old två today Stop Au Briton a blessing
tuổi två hôm nay Stop Au  Briton một b blessing
TOver 100 years,11 safeguard
TOver 100 năm,11 safeguard
idas s mattered
idas s mattered
psay
psay
call indicates
呼 indicates
Armenian ruler
quản Armenian
Everyone knows that Xiaoyuan is
各位都知道 知晓媛是
Zheyan Rescue
浙岩救援
very important
非常重要的
an activity
一个活动
have been around for a long time
行之有年
every month
每个月
all early
都早
in various fields
在各领域里面
most academically accomplished
最有学术成就的
experts and scholars
专家学者
Some are from our courtyard
有的是我们院里面的
some are
有的是
various university societies
各个大学社会
the following
下面的这些
academia
学术界的人士
come talk to everyone
来跟大家谈
in various fields
各个领域里面
latest development
最新的发展
i think today we
我想今天我们
very happy
非常高兴
also very honored
也很荣幸
please come
请到
Zheyan Rescue
浙岩救援
current director of the Institute for Statistical Science
現任的統計科學研究所的所長
Dr. Li Kezhao came to tell you
李克昭博士來跟大家講
The subject of our knowledge experiment this time
這一次的我們的知識想驗的課題
Dr. Li graduated from the Mathematics Department of National Taiwan University
李博士是台大數學系畢業的
He went to the University of California, Berkeley
他去美國加州伯克萊大學
Practicing a Ph.D.
練了博士
practicing statistics
練的是統計學
He is in residence at the University
他在普駐大學
Go to UCLA
去UCLA加州洛杉磯分校
Institute of Statistics
統計所擔任教職
So he's basically UCLA's over there
所以他基本上是UCLA的他的在那边
From Professor Zhu to Distinguished Professor
从朱教授一直到后来是Distinguished Professor
Professor Li is engaged in the research of statistical theory
李教授他从事的是统计理论方面的研究
His academic contributions are very high
他的学术上的贡献成就非常高
His greatest and most admired contribution by the statistical community is in his most
他最大的被统计界最推崇的贡献是在他最于
What is the Chinese translation? Multi-variate high-dimensional
中文翻译下是什么?Multi-variate high-dimensional
Statistical Analysis of Variables in High Dimensions
高维住的变量的统计的分析
The main reason is that the actual
主要的原因是在实际的
in the data used
使用的数据里面
Whether it is experimental or natural data,
不管是实验或者是自然界产生的数据里面
many probably almost mostly high dimensional
很多可能几乎大部分都是高维度的
Then ordinary statistical methods to study this
那普通的统计方法去研究这个
is always flawed
始终是有缺陷
So everyone thought of many different ways
所以大家想了很多种不同的办法
To use statistical methods to analyze such complex data
去把统计的办法用来做这种复杂的数据的分析
Neither was very successful
都不是很成功
Dr. Li invented a method in the 1990s
李博士在90年代发明了一套办法
It is recognized by everyone as doing this thing
就被大家公认是做这件事情里面
One of the most effective and best ways
最有效最好的办法之一
So his contribution in this aspect is really quite big.
所以他在这方面的贡献确实蛮大
In the last ten years or so, he has put his interest in biostatistics,
最近十年吧,他把他的信趣放在生物統計上面,
The achievements above are also very large.
這上面的成就也非常大。
Since he returned to Taiwan six years ago and served as the director of the ten-year research institute,
他六年前回台灣回國以後,在十年研究院擔任所長以來,
With Taiwanese scholars, especially Taiwanese medical scholars,
跟台灣的學者,尤其是台灣的醫學界的學者,
Cooperate with doctors who actually work and use the latest statistical methods,
跟實際工作的醫生們合作用最新的統計的方法,
Do very difficult, but also very important analysis of biological and medical data.
做非常困難的,但是也非常重要的生物和醫學方面的資料的分析。
He and the very outstanding scholars of National Taiwan University,
他跟台大的非常優秀的學者,
Including Yang Pangci, the dean of the School of Medicine at National Taiwan University
包括現在台大的醫學院院長楊胖慈
Academician lung cancer group
院士肺癌的group
made recent quite groundbreaking research results
做了最近有相當突破性的研究成果
These results have been used in practical medicine
這些成果都已經陸續用在實際的醫學上面
Medical top
醫療上面
Today he talked about this topic
今天他就這方面的題目
apply other statistical methods
應用他統計的方法
Statistical processing and analysis of genetic technology information
做基因科技資訊的統計處理分析
He called him chaos
他把他說是亂中有序
let's welcome him
我們來歡迎他
I choose this topic today
我今天選這個題目
The first aspect is my interest
第一方面是我的興趣
On the other hand, because I know the words of this talk
另外一方面是因為我知道這個talk的話
There are many different backgrounds for this listener
是針對這個聽眾有很多不同的background
When it comes to statistics, most people are in awe of three points
說到統計大部分的人都是敬畏三分
My cesar advisor is called prof. Jack Heaver
我的cesar advisor叫做prof. Jack Heaver
He is also a National Academician of the United States unfortunately a year early four
他也是美國國家院士不幸一年早四
He once said that when he was flying
他有一次說他坐飛機的時候
There's a lady sitting next to me
旁邊就坐了一位淑女
Then the two of you chatted and it was very interesting
然後兩個人聊來聊非常有趣
what do you do
問到你做什麼
He said I was a professor of statistics
他說我是統計的教授
Immediately stand alone
馬上台獨一邊
i hate statistics
我最討厭統計人人的
Because statistics have a whole bunch of companies
因為統計有一大堆公司
How is it? I don't know what's going on inside
怎麼樣子搞不懂裡頭在幹嘛
The words in my talk today
我今天的talk裡頭的話
I want to change your point of view
我是想轉變各位的觀點
Because statistics are actually because there are many such computers and so on.
因為統計其實因為現在有很多這個電腦等等的
Can help you deal with those company issues
可以幫你處理那些公司的問題
Your company doesn't need to memorize it, you only need to memorize it once
你公司用不著記 你只要記一次就好
The rest of the things are called pressing a button and everything comes out.
就要剩下的東西就叫按一個鍵什麼東西都出來
So what the memory worker is is not a very important key
所以記憶工是什麼並不是一個很重要的關鍵
The most important key is statistical thinking
最重要關鍵是統計的思維
This is a fairly logical thinking
這個是一種一種相當邏輯的思考
Then this processing data
那這個處理資料
You see or see some information in the society, etc.
你看或是在社會上看到一些情報等等的
I hope that it can have this statistical spirit in it
我希望說是能夠有這種統計的精神在裡頭
Then see a lot of that
那就看到很多的那個
It's a social thing and you'll keep it in your heart
是社會的東西你就會心存以
The most basic characteristic of that statistician
那個統計學家最基本的特色
He just won't believe him when he sees the information
就是看到資料他不會去相信他
He will answer a big question mark
他都會答一個大的 question mark
so
所以
Is it really like that?
到底是真的是那樣子嗎
Then I think today although I use the
那我想今天雖然我用的是
This biotechnology information
這個生物科技方面的資料
Then I hope that the last message brought to you is a concept
那我希望那個最後的訊息帶給各位的是一個concept
Everyone can use it in daily life
大家可以用在日常生活上面
Thanks
謝謝
Well, that gene we all know now
好 那個我們都知道現在的基因
science is very advanced
科學非常發達
The species that says mostly a lot cannot say most
那個說大部分很多的物種不能說大部分
The sequencing of the genes of many species has come to an end
很多物種的基因的定序都已經告一段系列了
And what about the next job?
然後接下來的工作呢
biologists rely on some so-called vitamin
生物學家就靠了一些所謂的維生物製片
this way or vitamin glyconucleic acid
這個這樣子或是維合糖核酸
And some Next Generation
還有一些Next Generation
This is something that the second generation is sequenced to and so on
這是第二代定序於等等的東西
generate a lot of data
製造很多的數據
Use it to help with complex diseases such as cancer
拿來幫助做一些癌症等複雜疾病等
research or you are in crops you want to change its important shape
研究或者是你在農作物你要改變它重要的形狀
For example, genetic factors such as endurance, high yield, etc.
比如說是耐行啊然後多產量等等的這個遺傳的因子
So in so many different fields
那在這這麼多的這個不同領域裡頭
Different in the domain of this creature
不同的這個生物的領域裡頭
Everyone uses especially the same nature of these materials
大家都用的尤其都是同樣的性質的這些資料
Then how to rely on this computer to wait for this
那如何去靠著這個電腦等等的這個
grant to do this analysis of the data
補助來做資料的這個分析
find out the rules
發現這裡頭的規律
Well that's an interesting question for the guy we do the stats
那這就是那個我們做統計的人一個很有趣的問題
Because there are so many variables involved
因為這裡頭牽涉到的變數非常之多
So today I mainly give some simple examples to introduce to you.
那所以我今天主要是舉一些簡單的例子來跟各位做介紹
And when it comes to statistics, like the average person pays this head on
那談到統計那像一般人付出這個腦海裡頭
It's like this striking power, like Wang Jianmin's
就是像這個打擊力啊像王建民的
It depends on how much impact you need.
打擊力要算好就多少等等的
or some polls
或者是一些民意的調查
Like how many people win a certain policy
像某一個政策有多少人戰勝多少
while opposed to etc.
而反對等等的
then why did i choose to do this
那我為什麼選擇做這個
biology
biology 生物
This time the most important thing is
這次最主要是
because according to many people
因為根據很多人說
The so-called 21st century is
所謂的21世紀是
Nero, Bio, Info
Nero, Bio, Info
that is to say
也就是說是
Nero is Namimi's technology
Nero就是能耐米的科技
Then Bio is biology
然後Bio就是biology
Info is information
Info就是資訊方面的
The so-called three major technologies of the 21st century
所謂的21世紀的三大科技
Of course statistics are not here
當然統計不是這裡頭
very frivolous
非常沾閃邊
Then I chose this piece because of this
那我選擇這一塊就是因為這個
biology he is gradually changing
biology他逐漸在轉換之中
that he
那他
by some of the past
是由過去的一些
Probably some observations and some more qualitative
大概就是一些觀察一些比較定性
east and west
的東西
Record what this thing is when you see it
看到這個東西是什麼東西就記錄下來
Work like that gradually
那樣子的工作逐漸
Doing some rather quantitative reason is quite quantitative
做一些相當quantitative的reason就是相當定量的
need to make some inferences
需要做一些推論的
this kind of work
這種工作
That's what makes this a lot of mathematicians including statistics
那這就是讓這個很多的數學家包括統計
Mathematicians, including scientists, have a lot of room for this activity
學家在內的數學家有很大的這個活動的空間
Then we can use some of our thinking abilities
然後我們就可以利用我們的一些思考能力
come to help
來幫忙
this from this
這個從這個
huge amount of this
巨量的這個
Find some rules in financial data
金融的data裡頭去發現一些規律來
The human genome is
human genome就是
This financial project
金融的這個project
It was roughly completed around the beginning of 2000 AD
大概是差不多在公元2000年初的時候就已經大致完成
The main thing is to do some regular work
最主要是做一些定期的工作
that in that respect
那在那方面的話
At the beginning, everyone thought there were about 30,000 gold
當初的時候大家認為大概有三萬個金左右
But now it turns out that there aren't that many
不過現在發現事實上是沒有那麼多
More than 30,000 gold is mainly based on some knowledge at that time
三萬多個金主要是根據那時候的一些知識
Estimated from some computers
根據一些computer 電腦估計出來的
Then this slide was produced by the US Department of Energy
那這一張slide是美國的這個能源部製作的
Originally promoted this project
原來宣導這個project
Then the remaining problems after decoding begin
那這個解碼以後剩下來的問題才開始
Because there are twenty-five thousand gold
因為有兩萬五千個金
What is the function of each gold?
那每個金它的功能是怎麼樣子的
Then is it in the genome world
然後是不是在基因體世界
Different genes can form a functional body
不同的基因能夠形成一個功能體
between the different functions
那不同的功能體之間
What is its interactive relationship like?
它的互動的關係到底是怎麼樣子
Then there are two-year-old cells
然後有兩歲細胞啊
How do you use these genes to regulate his metabolism?
怎麼樣子利用這些基因來調控他的這個新陳代謝啊
issues of growth
成長等等的問題
Then there are many problems
那這個問題還很多
a bunch of these
這些一大堆這個
Iton, I can’t talk to each and every one of you
Iton我沒辦法每一個每一個都跟各位
introduce
介紹
That
那
So from
所以呢就從
In basic biology, there is probably an idea that it is hoped that the
基礎生物學上面大概就有想到說希望把
use these genes
利用這些基因
This information about genes
跟基因有關的這個資料
Then form a science
然後組成一門學問
then research this
然後研究這個
The various components in this cell
這個細胞裡頭各個不同的成分
Then
然後
To describe which gene has how much?
去描述說哪一個基因有多少量啊
then when does he show it
然後他在什麼時候表現出來
What is the result of his performance and his influence?
那他表現的結果他的影響是怎麼樣子的
Wait, make a big, big mathematical model
等等的弄一個很大很大的數學模型
Then right on the computer you might be able to
然後就在電腦上面你可能可以
Even make a so-called Virtual Cell
甚至弄成一個所謂的Virtual Cell
just one by one
就是一個一個
imaginary this
假想的這個
cell but
細胞但是
The function inside is just like the performance inside
裡頭的功能就跟裡頭的表現出來
It is exactly the same as normal real cells
就是跟一般的真實的細胞完全一廟
So it's a fairly
所以這是一個相當
It's a pretty great one
可以說是相當偉大的一個
enough for me to be there
夠我在那裡頭
Hope to be able to do some cells
希望能夠做一些細胞
How do you respond to external stimuli?
對外在的刺激能夠有怎麼樣的反應
But before accomplishing such a great task
可是在達成這樣子一個偉大任務之前
This Medical Research
這個Medical Research
In fact, it is more advanced
事實上是走在更前端
they can't wait
他們已經不能等了
Because if you want to do this basic scientific research
因為要做這個基礎的科學的研究的話
Nothing to do with practicality
沒有牽涉到實用上面
In fact, there is no support from any government
事實上只得不到任何政府的支持了
Because it is a complex disease with many direct
因為是直接很多的複雜的疾病
Everyone thinks it has something to do with genes
大家都認為跟基因有關係
what is the relationship
那到底關係在哪裡
how to use these
如何利用這些
Although the knowledge of this gene body of the incisor just now
雖然剛剛門牙的這種基因體的這個知識
is able to do some help
是能夠做一些幫助
just inside
就是在裡頭
I will list one here
我這邊就列出一個
Currently doing the easiest to identify
目前做的最容易被identify
a doable goal
一個可行的一個目標
so-called molecular diagnosis
就是所謂的分子診斷
is the traditional words
就是傳統上的話
according to the pathologist
根據病理學家看看
this slice and so on
這個切片圖等等
make some judgments
去做一些判斷
Judgments like that are often wrong
那樣子的判斷常常會有誤
Method doesn't get enough queries
方式得到的質詢不夠多
So now based on some molecular
所以現在就是根據一些分子的
The method is through some genetic
方法就是透過一些基因的
performance measurement
表現量的檢測
See if there are any mutations in the gene, etc.
看基因有沒有突變等等的
do some diagnostics
去做一些診斷
Then
然後
So his goal is to hope that this
所以他的目標是希望這個
Physicians can use this
醫師可以在這個
Before diseased tissue stroke
病變組織行程之前
can predict
就能夠預測到
express like cancer cells are
表示像癌細胞是
it might happen etc.
有可能發生等等的
and then further able to
然後進一步能夠對
The medical quality of treatment has
治病的醫療品質上面有
substantial improvement
大幅的改善
and then even
然後甚至
Someone mentioned whether your genes are bad
有人提到是不是你的基因不好
I can help you remodel and so on.
可以幫你改造改造等等的
Then when we talked about how to do this analysis
那在我們談到說如何去這個分析
Such complex information on this gene was previously
這麼複雜的這個基因的資料之前
We must have some of the most basic of this
我們一定要有一些最最基本的這個
Ballage Background
Ballage Background
So I'll post it in a few minutes
那所以我底下就發幾分鐘時間來
Soon Goal through these so-called Knowledge
很快的Goal through這些所謂的Knowledge
So if this is the case
所以這樣子的話
We have some consensus in the talk below
我們在底下的Talk就有一些共識
Then one of the most basic biological
那這個生物上一個最基本的
a so-called law
一個所謂的定律
A dogma is its message
一個教條就是它的這個資訊的
It's inside the organism called the cell
就是在細胞這個生物體裡頭
Its communication The communication of this instruction is from
它的傳達這個指令的傳達是從
this DNA
這個DNA
Then inside this chromosome
然後這個染色體裡頭
Then this DNA
然後這個DNA
Chrysostom
就是所謂的金口
Then after this transcription is transferred to
然後經過這個transcription就是轉入
into this messenger RNA
轉入成這個messenger RNA
messenger RNA
messenger RNA
Then translate into this protein after translation
再經過翻譯轉譯成這個protein
is our protein
就是我們蛋白質
Some biological functions are carried out by proteins
由蛋白質去執行一些生物上面的功能
That is of course a dogma here
那當然在這邊是一個教條
For everything in biology, there are examples and there must be counterexamples.
所有生物上的東西有例子一定有反例子
So there are counterexamples
所以有反例子
So there are quite a few cases like this one
所以有不少的這個情況這樣子的一個
information flow will be
information flow是會被
not complied with
不被遵守的
that that
那那個
you open a cell
你打開一個細胞
Fetch something from the cell when it makes sense
從細胞合理的時候取出來一些東西
The most important component is the chromosome
最重要的成分就是染色體
Chromosome words
染色體的話
We all know it is through
我們都知道它是透過
Four different nucleotide compositions
四個不同的核幹酸組成
ATG type
ATG型
that's a pair
那這是成對的
Then it's highly congruent
那它的結會性很高
These two will
這兩個會
If it is A, it must be received by T.
A的話一定要接到T
If it is G, it must be received by C.
G的話一定接到C
Then you don't understand people's words
那你不太懂的人的話
conceivably say yes
可以想像成說是
A is a relatively large
A的話是一個比較大的
This probably is
這應該是
Then T is relatively small
然後T是比較小
so one big and one small
所以一個大一個小
This way it matches Size
這樣子配合起來Size
That G is relatively large
那G是比較大的
That C is relatively small
那C是比較小
no symmetrical relationship
那無相對稱的關係
Then A cannot match G
那A不能夠對到G
etc.
等等
That gene is actually this
那基因事實上是這個
the whole this very long this
整個這個很長很長的這個
A short passage from ChromoSong
ChromoSong裡頭的一小段
a fragment of it
那它的一個片段
it has a message
它是帶有訊息的
kana order
かなorder
what is its message
它帶的訊息是什麼呢
based on these
就是根據了這些
Let's say your DNA is double-stranded
比如說你這個DNA是成雙股的
then you are single
那你單一股
For example, this stock is GCA
比如說這一股是GCA
GCA will be transferred
GCA就會被轉
translates to an amino acid
轉譯成一個胺基酸
We have a total of 20 different amino acids
我們一共有20個不同的胺基酸
20 amino acids are arranged and combined through ATGC
20個胺基酸就是經過ATGC這樣子的排列組合
translate it
把它翻譯出來
After talking about genes
那講完了基因之後
an important thing
重要的一個東西
It's this Messenger
是這個Messenger
ribonucleic acid
就是訊息的核糖核酸
What is message RNA
訊息核糖核酸是什麼呢
It is a certain segment in this DNA
它是這個DNA裡頭這個某一段
Especially in this part of the gene
尤其是在基因的這一段
near the gene
靠近基因的這一段
it will have a
它會有一個
This mechanism puts the ATGC of this section
這個機制把這一段的ATGC
make a copy of it
把它做一個copy
copy over
copy過來
Then this copy will be sent outside the cell box
然後把這個copy會送到這個細胞盒外面
Then go through this Ribosol
然後經過這個Ribosol
Ribosol imagined as a large
Ribosol想像成一個大型的
processing plant a manufacturing machine
加工廠一個製造機器
It can put this oil slick in the cytoplasm
它可以把這個浮油在細胞質裡頭
Some amino acids hold it together piece by piece like this
一些胺基酸把它一塊一塊這樣結合在一起
According to your ATGC
根據你這個ATGC
It will look for those relative Amino Acid
它就會去找那些相對的Amino Acid
snap it out like this
把它這樣扣出來
So there's nothing wrong with that
所以這樣子的話就不會有錯
So this is a natural structure like this
所以這個是一個天然的這樣子一個結構
That is, a certain section of your ATGC will be automatically translated
就是你ATGC的某一段就會被自動翻譯出來
I just said that's right
我剛剛講說沒錯
In fact all living organisms
事實上所有的生物體的話
In fact, there are quite a lot of mistakes
事實上錯誤是蠻多的
is a lot
是不少
Then it will have some correction mechanism
那這些它就會有一些這個Correction的機制
The words there are also a great knowledge
那裡頭的話又是一個很大的學問
This is a different version of what I just said.
這個呢就是把剛剛講的又從一個不同的這個
This view wing map is the nucleus.
這個視翼圖弄出來就是細胞核啊
Then through this transfer work from the gene
然後經過這個轉移的工作從基因裡頭
Why do cells need to do the job of transferring
細胞為什麼需要做轉移的工作
At first I thought it was strong
初期想起來是很強的
Because you are inside the Cromosome of the Code of DNA
因為你這個DNA之Code的Cromosome裡頭
If you use this Ribos every time
如果你每次要用這個Ribos
What you want to transfer is directly from this gene
你要去轉移的都從這個基因裡頭直接
If the code comes out directly
直接Code出來的話
The original one is often used
那這個原來的那個常常會被用
So he can be easily damaged
所以他很容易就會被損壞掉
It doesn't matter if you destroy this Messenger IM
那你損壞掉這個Messenger IM沒關係
because you regenerated
因為你從新重基因的話
You can also copy one more
還可以再copy一個
So this is a pretty clever design
所以這是一個相當巧妙的一個設計
At the same time, in higher organisms
同時呢在高等的生物裡頭
it has a nucleus
它有細胞核
Then the outer words are the cytoplasm
然後外面的話是細胞質
So these Messenger IMs will be sent out
所以這些Messenger IM會被送出來
so inside it won't
所以在裡頭就不會
There will be a state of traffic chaos
會形成一個交通混亂的狀態
So we just talked about this protein
那我們剛剛談到這個蛋白質
Protein is made up of 20 Armino-S
蛋白質就是由20個Armino-S所組成的
A series of Armino-S for sightseeing
觀光這樣子一串的Armino-S
Actually it doesn't work by itself
事實上是本身不管用的
it relies on some of its
它是靠著它裡頭的一些
interaction near each other
彼此附近的交互作用
Form a so-called Protin Fold
形成一個所謂的Protin Fold
it has to be folded into a shape
它要折疊成一個樣子出來
this shape it is
這個形狀它是
The most important protin is relying on its shape
最主要的Protin是靠著它這個形狀
Is there a hole in it or something?
裡頭是不是有一個洞等等的
To determine its nature
來Determinate它的這個性質
words like this are
像這個的話是
This is to show
這個是表示出
A synthetic beauty called ATD inside the force line body
一個叫做力線體裡頭的ATD的合成美
ATD is what we call Hot Cache of Energy
ATD是我們所謂的Hot Cache of Energy
thermal diving
就是熱潛
if you want to generate fuel
就是你要產生燃料的話
You must go through ATD
你一定要透過ATD
This one in the vertical line is a synthesis of ATV
在立線裡頭的這個做ATV的一個合成
In this two different this
在這個兩種不同的這個
There is an EcoLine in the bio, which is what the large intestine looks like inside
生物裡頭這邊是一個EcoLine就是大腸感覺裡頭長的這個樣子
the words on the left
那左邊的話
I didn't write this here like a monkey or an orangutan
這邊我沒寫這個好像是一個猴子或是一個猩猩
They look the same, but they are actually very similar, although the level of this creature is much different.
長的一樣其實非常像雖然這個生物的等級差那麼多幾
But it's fairly consistent on the most basic units
可是在最基本的單位上面它是相當一致的
At the same time, it can be seen that the ProtinBis attachment I just mentioned
那這邊同時看出來我剛剛講過那個ProtinBis附相
very church made form
非常教會做形成
attached to a different this shape
附成一個不同的這個形狀
It's like a jigsaw puzzle, especially so this
很像拼圖一下尤其所以這個
this is a very interesting question
這是一個非常有趣的問題
OK
OK
The other more interesting question is that we have the same memory
那另外一個更有趣的問題是我們有同樣的記憶
We know that after the combination of the heavy bag and the gold side of the egg
我們就知道重包和這個卵子金子那邊結合之後
This one cell begins to divide
這個一個細胞就開始分裂
Those cells will grow into different tissues
那細胞會長成不同的組織
The DNA in every tissue is actually the same
那每一個組織裡頭的DNA事實上都是一樣的
then you will wonder why
那你會懷疑說那為什麼
The shape of the nose is different from the glasses
鼻子的樣子就是跟眼鏡不一樣
The cells in there are exactly the same
那裡頭的細胞完全一模一樣
That is how the matter
那是怎麼回事
The mechanism is in the expression of this gene
那其中的這個機制就在這個基因的表現
Because you will form a different organization
因為你會形成不同的這個組織裡頭
And the results of many different protins will be different
而且很多不同的Protin的成果會不一樣
Those protins are expressed by the wear debris gene
那些Protin是磨屑基因表現出來的
that's in a different organization
那在不同的組織裡頭
The expression of various genes will be relatively different
那各種基因的表現就相對的會不一樣
so in this
所以在這個
Slowly distribute from this embryo
從這個胚胎裡頭開始慢慢分發
it's a lot of fun
這是一個很有趣的
Which genes are expressed and when
在什麼時候哪些基因要被表現出來
Anyway, those things are formed first
反正那些什麼東西形成在前
what is formed after
什麼東西形成在後
That's a whole lot of knowledge
這整個是一個相當大的學問
Biologists rely on data
生物學家就是靠著資料
Such a large data transfer
這樣的一傳大型的資料
Slowly and slowly make this thing out again
慢慢慢慢再把這塊東西做出來
I just talked about how cells receive external stimuli
剛剛有談到說是細胞怎麼接受外面的刺激
and then some reactions will come out
然後會做出一些反應出來
let it grow etc.
讓它能夠生長等等的
this is a wanton
這是一個肆意圖
It is to receive some stimuli from the outside in the biological cells
就是在生物細胞裡面從外面接受一些刺激
usually on the outermost part of the cell
通常在細胞最外的話
There are some proteins called receptor protein
有一些 protein 叫做 receptor protein
lean body
就是瘦體
will accept small molecules
會接受一些小小的分子
put this together
把它這個結合在一起
Then it will have some chemical management
然後它就會有一些化學管理
wait
等等的
and then at the end its ultimate goal
然後到最後它的終極目標
is it possible to send this message to
是能夠把這個訊息傳到
inside the nucleus
這個細胞核裡頭來
Then there will be some of this protein
然後會有一些這個 protein
These proteins are called transcription factors
這些 protein 叫做 transcription factor 的
The protein will bind to the DNA
的 protein 它會結合在這個 DNA 上面
Then bring a certain segment of the gene
那就帶到某一段的基因
This section of the gene it will
這一段的基因它就會
copied by this into this
被這個 copy 成這個
message says this
message 講這樣
Then through the message, there will be protein
那透過 message 講這樣就有 protein
then there will be some
然後就會有一些
The role of protein
protein 的作用
those effects
那這些作用
It can also drive and possibly interact with other protein
也可以帶動可能跟其他的 protein
driving combination etc.
帶動結合等等的
So accept this signal from the outside
所以接受外面的這個 signal
There are a lot of proteins, there are a lot of receptors
這個 protein 非常多這個受體非常非常多
So you can accept different signal
所以你可以接受不同的 signal
so which protein
所以哪一種 protein
Can
可以
What kind of signal does this accept
這個接受的哪種signal
Then what happens underneath
然後底下到底是產生怎麼樣的作用
This whole thing is called signal transduction
這整個東西叫作signal transduction
chain of information transfer
信息傳遞的鏈
This is something that biologists really want to know
這一塊也是生物學家非常希望知道的
That also relies on the so-called bi-information
那也是靠著所謂的這個bi-information
is what bioinformaticians are currently doing
就是生物資訊學家目前正在做
Let’s go back to what we just said that the entire length of Keelung has about three B-faces.
那回到我們剛剛講的說這個整個條基隆大概長度有差不多三個B臉
30 3 billion Nuclear type base failure
30 30億的Nuclear type base failure
So there is a lot of information in the words
所以裡頭的話的information非常多
Now we know that there are about 25,000 genes
那基因現在我們知道說大約有25000個左右
Then it occupies only a small part of Keelung
那它佔據的只是這個基隆的一小部分
But there is a so-called intro in this gene
但是這個基因裡頭有所謂的intro
There is so-called excel
有所謂的excel
intron is the useful part
intron是有用的部分
intron is the useless part
intron是沒有用的部分
extron is the useful part
extron是有用的部分
Then there are some permutations and combinations of these
那這些又有一些排列組合的問題
Then what is the outside of this gincoding doing?
然後這個gincoding的外面到底在幹什麼
I used to think it was junk
以前都認為是junk
But now it is very important
但是現在認為非常重要
Because there are some transcription factors
因為有一些transcription factor
to bind in front
要bind的在前面
Then if it says that it was stimulated by some fakes, etc.
那上面如果說是被一些假激發等等的
then it won't work
那它就沒有作用了
So there is a lot of research on that area.
所以那一塊的研究也非常非常多
So this transfer medicine
那所以這個轉移醫學
It is hoped that through these genes
是希望透過這些基因體上面
able to promote these
能夠推廣這些
Immediately be able to do something that can be done immediately
馬上能夠做一些目前即時可以做的
the most important job
那最重要的一個工作
Of course, is it the information
當然是是不是這些information
can be used to help patients survive
能夠拿來幫助病人的存活
survival of life
人生的存活
Of course there is some information
那當然是有些資訊
used to help patients survive
拿來幫助病人的存活
survival of life
人生的存活
of course live
當然要活下去
So the first question is to say
所以第一個問題就是說
Are you able to rely on the information
你是不是能夠靠這些資料
can be used to predict
能夠拿來預測
don't talk yet
先不要談
First predict to see how long he can survive the patient
先預測看看他能夠病人活多久
According to your comprehension
根據你領悟
no choice
沒選擇
From these materials
從這些資料
can be compared to the traditional for example
可以比傳統的比方說
Staging
Staging
you heard this
你聽到這個
stage of lung cancer
肺癌幾期幾期的
What is the approximate survival rate?
大概存活率怎麼樣
Is it better than those
是不是比那些
there is this pathologist
有這個病理學家
according to their tissue lesions
根據他們組織病變
See if he transfers and so on
看他有沒有轉移等等的得到
able to be more precise
能夠更精確
this is the first goal
這是第一個目標
And what about the second goal?
然後第二個目標呢
can you can
你可以是不是可以
according to your this
根據你的這個
Elite performance status
精英的表現的狀態
see if i use this drug
看看我如果用這種藥的話
how will he react
他會有怎麼樣的反應
He can
他會
more effective
比較有效
or less effective
或是比較沒有效
even
甚至呢
I hope to do some two-case detection
希望說是做一些二例detection
before the disease occurs
在病變還沒有發生之前
let's see if
我們先看看是不是
start soon
快開始了
Then try to do prevention
然後設法去做prevention
finally
最後呢
Of course, you can hope to improve your quality of life
當然是能夠希望能夠改善你的quality of life
quality of your life
你的生活的品質
Then we use the so-called this
那我們用的所謂的這個
What exactly is this resource?
這個資源到底是什麼東西呢
what can be used is
什麼東西可以用就是
this
這個
Biochemists have many techniques
生物化學家這些有很多的technique
Now this biotechnology can see a lot of data
現在這個生物科技上面可以見到很多的 data
probably which data
大概是哪些 data
my side
我這邊
just slightly
只是稍微
describe
描述一下
there is
就是有
micro array is
micro array就是
micro certificate list
微證列的
genetic information
基因的資料
Then there is another
然後還有一種
called
叫做
array CGS
array CGS
array CGS is fetched
array CGS是拿來
Probe says it's this
探測說是這個
DNA的 copy
DNA的 copy
it is known
我們都知道
that usually
那個通常
A Sale has two chromosons, that is, a pair
一個Sale都有都是兩個chromoson就是成對
If you card DNA, you have Kirby
卡DNA的話就是有卡比
but in some cases
但是在某些情況之下
no change etc.
沒有變變等等
It will be more than Number for this card
它會這個卡比Number會更多
For a certain paragraph it is
某一段的話它就
The reason for how to continue has been repeated many times
繼續怎麼樣的原因被重複了很多次
repeat a lot
重複一多的話
Then you will affect the expression of the last gene
那你會影響到最後的基因的表現
It's just that certain genes are overexpressed
就是某些基因表現特別多
Sometimes those Kabi Numbers suddenly decrease a bit
有些時候那些卡比Number突然就有點減少
That's the part that doesn't work
就是那一段沒有作用
or for no reason
或者是無言無故
when passing from one generation to the next
從上一代傳到下一代的時候
lost
丟失掉了
Then there is Single Nucretypulomorphism
那還有Single Nucretypulomorphism
This is a genetic variant
這個是基因的變異型
This piece is also quite a lot of information
這塊也是相當多的資料
Then there is something called Transcription Factor
那還有一些叫做Transcription Factor
Information about Binding Side
Binding Side的資料
is what we just mentioned
就是我們剛剛提到說這個
A Transcription Factor
一個Transcription Factor
Can Binding in this
可以Binding在這個
Where is this DNA
這個DNA哪個位置
什麼transcription factor by the way
什麼transcription factor by the way
this is a great knowledge
這是一個很大的學問
There are some techniques that can be used
有一些技術可以用
There is also one called micro-init
還有一個叫做micro-init
This is a violation of the peace talks
這是違和和談和算
those performance
的那些表現量
Very important
非常重要
That
那
this is currently
這個是目前
The so-called very, very popular one that everyone talks about is very expensive.
所謂大家談的非常非常熱門的一個就是但是非常貴
that is
就是
This sequence in the new century
新世紀的這個sequence
He took this test
他是拿來這個測
a whole genome of this
一整整的基因體的這個
DNA
DNA
each nuclear
每個nuclear
can order it out
可以把它定序出來
In the past, this was an impossible, almost impossible task.
以前的話這個是一個不可能幾乎不可能的任務
Too much
太多了
but now
可是現在
you actually
你居然
can be in about a week or two
可以在差不多是一兩個禮拜
you can put your gene
就可以把你的這個基因
genetic
基因的
All the nuclear all take you
所有的nuclear全部都把你
order out
定序出來
This progress is very open
這個進步非常開
but still quite expensive
但是還是蠻貴的
Then my most important thing today is
那我今天最主要的就是
focus on this
focus on this
micro rate of this technique
micro rate of this technique
that many other this
那很多其他的這個
Race, CHF, SNP
Race, CHF, SNP
His basic spirit is the same as this
他的basic精神跟這個一樣
that next generation
那next generation
He made it completely different
他弄的它是完全不一樣的
technique
technique
But we use some statistical methods
但是我們用到一些統計方法
can pass
都可以通的
use that
用到那方面去
micro
micro
This is a micro certificate column
這是一個微證列
This chip is certified
經位證列的這個晶片
it looks like this
它長的這個樣子
every place words
每一個地方的話
there is a spot of light
有一個光點
The brightness of this spot
那這個光點的亮度
represent this place
代表這個地方
it's early
它所年早到的
this
這個
This Messenger ion is bright
這個Messenger ion的亮
every imaginable
每一個你可以想像的
Every place is a carbon needle
每一個地方都是一個碳針
ours
我們那個
can put
可以把
All genes are one by one
所有的基因都一個一個
straight up here
直在這上面
because we already know its sequence
因為我們已經知道它的序列
Then
然後
that according to its this
那根據它的這個
on the DNA
DNA上面的
complementary binding
complementary binding
is A to G
就是A對到G
G to C
G對到C
so
所以
it can find its relative
它可以找它相對的東西
stick it on
把它黏上去
So the whole technology is already very mature.
所以這個整個技術已經是非常成熟了
so
所以
This microRNA can
這個microRNA就可以
because it's pretty much telling you how much the gene is expressed
因為它幾乎就是等於告訴你說這個基因表現了多少
How much is this gene expressed
這個基因表現了多少
so it can be used for many things
所以它可以用來做很多東西
mark this creature
做這個生物的標記
do this
做這個
with this
跟這個
With this biomarker some drugs can be developed
有了這個生物標記就可以開發一些藥物
We can use the expression of these genes to divide cancer
我們可以拿這些基因的表現量來做癌症的分裂
So it's very, very useful
所以它用途非常非常的多
Then this is just one of the earliest applications
那這個只是一個最早期的一個應用
The Elegant group of the Broad Institute in the United States made such a result very early
美國Broad Institute的Elegant group很早就做出來這樣子的結果
There are two different types of Leukemia related to leukemia
有關於白雪病的兩種不同的Lukimia
in terms of gene expression
在從基因的表現那樣上面
We find the set of genes
我們找到這一組的基因
Leukemia performance is relatively high
Lukimia表現比較高
In AML, it is the snow white disease of acute femoral water disease
在AML就是急性股水病的白雪病裡頭
low performance
表現比較低
Another set of genes is just the opposite
另外一組基因剛好相反
Since you can find genes like this
由於你可以找出這樣子的基因
So in the future you have to use it to judge that it is the ideal of this person.
所以以後你要拿來判斷說是這個人的理想
What type of this Rukimia got
得的是哪一種類型的這個Rukimia
by measuring the expression of these genes
就可以透過測量這些基因的這個表現量
make a judgment
做一個判斷
Then let me briefly introduce
那底下我簡單的介紹一下
This is mine just now
我的這個就是剛剛
Director Liu Fuye also mentioned this National Taiwan University
劉富業長也提到這個台大
That Professor Yang Panzi is currently the dean of this medical school
那個楊潘茲教授目前是這個醫學院的院長
What their research team is doing
他們的研究團隊在做的這個這個東西
that their most important
那他們最最主要的
is doing lung cancer research
是在做肺癌的研究
What about lung cancer?
那肺癌呢
in taiwan can
在台灣可以
There are two types of lung cancer
這個肺癌可以分兩類
is a small cell
就是一個是小細胞的
one is non-small cell
一個是非小細胞的
Anyway, of course there are other kinds
反正當然還有其他的種類
The current research
目前研究最
So the hot part is no longer small cells
所以熱絡的部分不再小細胞
Because non-small cells are more
因為非小細胞比較多
nephrocytes
那非小細胞
Non-small cells can be further divided into two categories
非小型細胞又可以分成兩類
One is an Arduino Castle
一個是阿迪諾卡斯諾瑪
adenocarcinoma of the lung
就是所謂的肺腺癌
Then the other is to ask for Squamous Cell Cancer
然後另一種就是要Squamous Cell Cancer
on-going cells
就是要臨狀的細胞
This pathology looks
這個病理上面看起來
This slice looks quite different
這切片上看起來是相當不一樣的
The length is also different
那長的位置也不一樣
Then this Arduino Castle
那這個阿迪諾卡斯諾瑪
The reason why there are so many researches
之所以研究的目前非常多
most importantly
最主要是
This epidemiology found that it is this
這個流行病學上面發現說是這個
female non-smoking
女性的不抽菸的
especially easy to get this kind of
特別容易得到這一種
That is to say, women do not smoke
也就是說是女性不抽菸
So if the doctor tells you that you have lung cancer
那如果醫生告訴你說你得到肺癌
The skin is definitely the fat gland
肌膚可以肯定的就是肥腺
Very few people will get the cells of this Scramers
很少人會得到這種Scramers的細胞
It is generally believed that smoking causes cancer
大家一般觀念都說是抽菸會自癌
that doesn't smoke
那不抽菸
why cancer
為什麼會自癌
It's still a pretty big puzzle
這還是一個相當大的謎題
that don't smoke especially women
那不抽菸尤其是婦女
got a specific type of cancer
得到的是某種特定的這種癌
Then his research
那他的這個研究
In medicine, that is now very popular.
在醫學上面那個是現在做的非常紅烈的
Especially when he discovered a drug
那尤其是他發現一種藥
is to do this with a mutation to EGF
是做這個對EGF有一種突變
A mutation in a gene called EGF
一種基因的突變叫做EGF
is a production technology
就是一種生產技術
lower level
下層
EpDemo
EpDemo
Ghost Factor
Ghost Factor
what is it called shrimp skin
叫什麼蝦皮
Shrimp tissue this
蝦皮組織的這個
to grow
生長
factor
因素
that kind of thing
那一種東西
Mostly in the outbound cell growth
最主要是在出境細胞的生長
It is used a lot in fermented products
在發酵品裡頭用的非常多
over there
那裡頭
a certain one
某一個
Nucre-Tide
Nucre-Tide
have a mutation
有一個突變
or was deleted
或者是被deleted掉
You have a drug with that mutation
你用那種突變的話就有一種藥
Very effective to keep your cancer under control
非常有效可以把你的癌症控制出來
so
所以
the whole
這整個
this
這個
above number 1
1號上面
or treatment
或者是治療上面
a very important discovery
一個非常重要的發現
That
那
Teach them the whole of this
講教授他們整個的這個
Most of this treatment of lung cancer
最這個肺癌的這個treatment
hope to do is
希望做到的是
be able to do this gine screaming first
能夠先做這個gine screaming
For example, I just mentioned that it is you if the gine
比方說我剛剛提到說是你如果 gine 裡頭
There are some legal
有一些一切法的
Then you can put the screen out
那你就可以把screen出來
Then there is a cure
那就有藥可治了
That opinion law is not the only mutation
那意見法不是唯一的突變
you may have other different mutations
你可能有其他的不同突變
Is that the opinionality of being able to discover other genes
那是不是能夠發現其他的基因的opinionality
Those structures that have mutations or mutations that are different from normal
就是突變或是變異跟平常不一樣的那些結構
Can be taken out as a target of your drag
能夠拿出來當成你的drag的一個target
Make something to target it with medicine
造一些對準它來下藥
Then this is currently hoping to find some drag targets
那這個目前是希望能夠發現一些drag的target
so what
所以呢
This you can do some early detection
這個你能夠做一些early detection
capable of some dalgonosis
能夠有些dalgonosis
Then mentioned many times here are all biomarkers
然後這裡頭提到的很多次就是所有的biomarker
Biomarker is required for screen early detection
在做screen early detection都要需要biomarker
The biomarker
這個biomarker
What about the biomarker we used?
那我們用到的這個biomarker呢
There are so many, you can have pictures, and then you can also use the expression of this gene, microRNA
非常多,你可以有圖片,然後也可以用這個gene的expression,microRNA
What about Teacher Yang's team, this
楊老師的團隊呢,這個
OK, that is BioMarket and so on, this has just been mentioned
OK,就是BioMarket等等,這個剛剛已經講過了
Teacher Yang and their greatest contribution is on this day
楊老師他們最大的貢獻是在這一天
The article is on New English Medicine, the first author is Chen Xuanyi
文章在New English Medicine上面,第一的作者陳軒儀
Currently serving in our unit, this is his work when he was a doctoral student at National Taiwan University
目前是在我們的單位服務,這個是他在台大當博士生的時候的作品
They found five genes, the five genes
他們找到五個gene,那這五個gene
What about the performance of your five genes, here
你的這個五個gene的這個表現量呢,這邊
This picture shows 13 genes, about 16 genes.
這一張圖是表現十三個gene,十六個gene左右,他
Finally, they found out from these sixteen genes, and finally found out five genes
最後又從這個十六個gene他們找出,最後是找出五個gene
Then according to the sixteen genes
那根據這個十六個gene
In terms of genes, you can see that the expression chain is relatively high
基因的話你可以看出來說是這個表現鏈比較高
The higher performance chain is yellow
表現鏈比較高的是用黃色
Some genes have a higher expression chain
有些基因表現鏈比較高
Making other genes high is a very good performance
讓另外一些基因的高是表現很標的
Then according to these heights?
那根據這些高低呢
It can do a math with the above formula
它可以做一個數學上面的公式
compress it to
把它加壓減減成
Then make a this to predict this
然後做出一個這個拿來預測這個
It's an indicator of the patient's survival
它這個病人存活的一個指標
The higher the number of months, the higher your risk
這個數月高的話你的風險就越高
Then they can prove from this clinical data that
然後他們可以從這個臨床的資料去證明說
What about the marker they got?
他們得到的這個這個marker呢
is very effective in distinguishing between the relatively low risk
是非常有效可以區分這個風險比較低的
higher risk
跟風險比較高的
What about this picture?
那這個圖呢
In fact, statistical biometrics
事實上是統計生物統計裡頭
One of the most famous pictures
最最出名的一個一種圖啊
It's called the shipping chart
就是叫做出貨圖
This picture of that CAP-CAP-MILLE
那個CAP-CAP-MILLE的這個圖
Then it reads as
那它的讀法就是
All your patients start out alive
你所有的病人剛開始的話都是活的
then learn
然後學著
In the course of time people start dying
時間的過程之中就開始有人死了
If one is not dead, he will drop one.
沒死一個他就掉一個掉一個這樣子
How much does it cost? This is learning to have one of this
那掉多少呢這是學有一個這個
There is a formula above the statistics
統計上面有一個公式
so fall faster
所以掉得越快
If you click more, it means your this
就越一下的話表示你的這個
is a risk
是一個risk
the greater the risk
就風險越大
So your low risk can hardly drop
所以你low risk幾乎不掉
high risk falls quickly
high risk掉得很快
Then Teacher Yang and their results
那楊老師他們的這個結果
then come in this
然後來在這個
data in the west
在西方的data
this nature
這個nature
There is a genetic medicine
有篇genetic medicine
2008 people this shedon
2008人這個shedon
They also mentioned in their works
他們的作品裡頭也提到
And then it turns out he's still just as effective
然後也證明他還是一樣有效
so no matter in
所以不管在中
Eastern sources in Western sources
東方的資料在西方的資料
It can also be used to do this
也一樣可以拿來做這個
This none small sale cancer
這個none small sale的cancer
this lone cancer
lone cancer的這個
BioMarket can be used to predict the survival of his patients
BioMarket可以拿來預測他的病人的存活
by the way SheddonLead author
by the way Sheddon第一作者
This is American is my former student at UCL
這是美國人是我以前在UCL的學生
Is it actually the author's side when he does it with me?
他跟我做的時候事實上是不是作者方面
he's just a statistician
他只是一個統計學家
He's in Michigan now
他現在在Michigan
He can actually be the first science in Natural Medicine
他居然可以在Natural Medicine上面當第一個科學
This article is very good
這一篇文章非常好
He is combining about four or five large American institutions to build the Long Cancer Center.
他就是結合大概有美國四五個大的做Long Cancer Center
the collected data
所集合的資料
bring it all together
把它全部都集合在一起
To see which way to predict patient survival
去看看哪一種預測patient的存活的方法
which one is better
哪一種比較好
Because stuff like suspense they do is just one way
因為像懸疑他們做的東西只是其中的一種方法
There are others who have different information and find out different methods
還有別人有不同的資料找出來不同的方法
Their article is to use different marks for direct comparison
他們這篇文章就是拿來不同的mark 直接拿來做比較
Another job is to do what's called microsugar
另外一個工作是做所謂的微糖
Micro ribonucleic acid is micro-init
微核糖核酸 就是micro-init
micro-init is a little bit bigger than normal Messingale
micro-init是一個小小的比普通的Messingale
It only has about 22 nucleotides
它大概只有22個nucleotide
With so compact micro-init
用那樣子小型的micro-init
Generally speaking, it is believed that it can be attached to some Messingale
一般的話都是認為它能夠去附著在一些Messingale
The above init can destroy it or make it non-transferable
init的上面能夠把它破壞掉或是讓它不能夠轉移
So it has a regulatory effect on this gene
所以它這個基因上面有調控的作用
So while making a lot of Messingale like this
所以雖然造了很多Messingale這樣
In principle, it is to be translated into Protin
原則上是要把它翻譯成Protin
Bringing out INA is equivalent to killing you or destroying your entire project.
把INA出來等於是把你殺掉等於把你這整個工程
make you a whole can
把你做一個整罐
So this MICRO-INA is very important
所以這個MICRO-INA是非常重要的
Although it is a small tax
雖然是個子稅小
Tax is small, people are small, ghosts are big
稅小 人小 鬼大
According to this article
那根據這篇文章
This is our team with that
這是我們的團隊跟那個
Yang Panzi's team worked on this Consol Cell
楊潘子團隊做在這個Consol Cell上面
Just find these five MICRO-INA
就找到這五個這個MICRO-INA
and then do the same
然後也是做同樣的工作
Find a RISC score
找出一個RISC score
This RISC score is also based on Cox Regression here
這個RISC score也是由這邊根據Cox Regression
is a method of biostatistical analysis
就是一個生物統計分析的方法
go find it this
去找出它的這個
The degree of influence on the survival of this certainty
對這個定能存活的影響的程度
and then give it a different weight
然後給它一個不同的weight
different weight
不同的這個比重
Then find out a RISC score like this
然後找出一個這樣子的一個RISC score
Then you look at the place where the RISC score is higher
那你看這個RISC score越高的地方的話
This side is this time of survival
這個這邊是這個存活的時間
The same color means dead, most of the dead are more
同色是代表死的,是大部分的死的比較多
At the same time, the living time is relatively small
同時這個活的時間也比較小
A little less, life is higher here
少一點,這邊活的比較高
If the soil is like this, in fact
那這樣子的土的話,其實
Without some statistical analysis
如果說是沒有經過一些統計的分析
Originally speaking, it was very messy at all.
本來的話是根本就是非常亂
Then here is according to this certain order
那這邊是根據這個一定的排序
It must be added so that you can see it
一定加成你才可以看出來
This looks very orderly
這樣子一個很有秩序的樣子
Then of course you can also put a different marker
那你當然也可以把不同的這個marker
put it together
把它集合在一起
For example you can put this
比方說你可以把這個
Use gene expression and this micro as a combination
用基因表現量跟這個micro來把它做為一個結合
can get this shipped
可以得到這個出貨的
This prediction can do better
這個prediction能夠做得更好
OK, so to put it simply
OK,所以簡單講起來
through life support data
透過維生數據
The future theme is mainly hope from the patient
將來的主題主要是希望從病人裡頭
draw blood, etc.
抽取力血等等的
then go through this
然後經過這個
microarray
micro array
You just put the number of this gene
你就把這個基因的這個個數
order out
訂出來
Then do some math analysis
然後做一些數學的分析
then you can bring
然後就可以拿來
look at yours
看看你的這個
how is the current situation
目前的狀況帶怎麼樣
It probably depends on how advanced the disease is, etc.
大概是疾病的進展程度如何等等的
or
或是
OK
OK
good
好
Then the many effects we just mentioned
那我們剛剛提到的不少的作用
then i want that now
那我現在希望那個
make a
做一個
a little summary
稍微的總結
Then I hope that today I can give you
然後希望今天能夠給各位
There is a relatively healthy
有一個比較康可的
because I just kept saying
因為我剛剛一直提到說
we can do this
我們可以做這些
that some and every time you mention these things say
那一些 然後每次提到這些東西都說
There can be statistical methods and so on, and at the end it will be your result
可以有統計方法等等 然後到最後就乾你結果
like that i think
那樣子的話 我想
There is no deep-rooted effect, but if I say that I want to
沒有一些刻骨的作用 但是我如果說要把
All in all, there are too many companies, so
所有的東西都講的話 又有太多公司了 所以
I decided to just tell you guys
我決定底下只是跟各位講一下
Some very important concepts. What about this concept?
一些一個很重要的觀念 那這個觀念呢
Can be used on this gene to behave like that
可以用在這個基因表現那樣上面
At the same time, you can also take it home and use it in your other
同時呢 你也可以帶回家用在你其他的
life or you deal with other data above
生活 或者是你處理其他的資料上面
Then I hope to be able to do something like this
那我希望能夠做到這樣子的工作
good
好
Let's start from here
那就從這個這邊開始講一下
Science is usually advanced and depends on some
Science通常是advanced都是靠的一些
info
info
inferences, make some inferences
推論,一定要做一些推論
These inferences are usually drawn from some already known
這些推論呢,通常是從一些已經知道的
or partially known, to speculate on those who do not know
或是部分知道的,去推測那些不知道的
or partially know
或是部分知道的
that in this statistician
那在這個統計學家裡頭
that they often use a method
那個他們常用到一個辦法
is to use some so-called this
就是用一些所謂的這個
random, Marko-random model to
random, Marko-random model來
is that you put each variable
就是你把每一個變數
each variable as a
每一個變數當成一個
Treat it as a node like this
在這邊當成一個這樣子的一個node
With this, A is a variable
用這個,就是A是一個變量
B is a variable
B是一個變量
This R is a parameter etc.
這個R是一個參數等等的
Then this variable can control the variables below, etc.
那這個變量可以控制底下的變量等等的
Well, the statistics are more interesting
那,統計比較有趣的
that's what they do
就是他們會去做這樣子的
a corollary that can do something like this
一個能夠做這樣子的一個推論
That is, if I talk about the variable A
就是我現在如果說對A這個變量
I can get some data
我可以得到一些數據
For the variable C, some data can also be obtained
對於C這個變量也可以得到一些數據
E is also available
E也可以得到
D is also available
D也可以得到
But I don't know R and V
但是我不知道R跟V
these are my interesting
這些是我interesting
Through some so-called Bation of computation
透過一些所謂的Bation of computation
This calculation method of Base
Base的這個計算方法
If you already know this before and after
如果說你已經知道這些前後之間的這個
relationship words
關係的話
it can go backwards
它可以倒退回去
You can get what is the variable in this R
可以得到這個R裡頭這個變數到底是怎麼樣
That
那
But a structure like this
但是這樣子的一個結構
pro set is
親設到的就是
First
第一個
There are quite a lot of these nodes in the biological system
在生物的系統裡頭這些nodes相當多
That
那
at the same time
同時呢
You know a lot
你知道的雖然已經不少了
Let's say you now have 25,000 genes
比方說你現在有兩萬五千個基因
You now have 25,000 nodes all know
你現在有兩萬五千個nodes都知道
but there are many things in it
但是裡頭有很多的東西
don't even know
更不知道
There will be more things I don't know
不知道的東西會更多
So there are many of this dimension
所以就有很多這個dimension的這個
some problems
有的問題
how to overcome this
那如何去克服這種
Dimension Difficulty
Dimension的困難
On Base Computation
在Base Computation上面
great progress so far
目前就很大的進展
Statisticians invest a lot
統計學家投入了很多
Many so-called MCMC Algorithms
很多所謂的MCMC的Algorithm
what about that part
那一部分呢
I won't talk about him here
我在這邊就不去講他
That's what I just mentioned about Macopher's
就是我剛剛提到這個Macophere的
this principle
這個原理
So what I want to talk about today is
那我今天比較想講的是
This is the comparison
這個就是比較
as a more general
作為一般更管方用的
just don't need to say yes so carefully
就是不需要那麼仔細說是
I have to know this identification
我已經要知道這個辨識
Which one to identify
跟哪一個辨識
what kind of relationship
怎麼樣的關係
This is comparing a Generic Purpose
這是比較一個Generic Purpose
This is the relationship between identification and identification
就是這個辨識跟辨識的關係
I do not know anything
我什麼都不知道
I don't need to make any assumptions
我不需要做任何假設
then you can fetch
然後可以去拿來
Do this to maintain the drop-down above
做這個維護上面的降位
It's just that I have a lot of information
就是我原來資料非常多
But according to these common methods
但是根據這些普通的方法
we can reduce it to its dimension
我們就可以把它降低它的維度
Comparably capable of mastering these data
比較能夠對這些數據比較能夠掌握
Then there are several ways
那這有幾個方法
One is Principle Component composition analysis
一個是Principle Component組成分析
Factor Analysis
Factor Analysis
And then there's the division of powers and so on.
然後還有分權法等等的
Behind these methods
那在這幾個方法裡頭的背後
In fact, the most important concept is
其實最重要的一個觀念就是
Correlation
Correlation
That's because there are many variables
那因為變數很多
So different Correlation is a lot
所以不同的Correlation就是一大堆
Then it looks like a matrix
那這邊就成一個矩陣的樣子
It is Correlation Matrix
就是Correlation Matrix
Then this Correlation
那這個Correlation
You can also look at it from another angle
也可以換一個角度來看
It can also be regarded as similarity
也可以把它當成相似度
Large and polyphasic
不同變數的大與有多相
High Correlation indicates that the two verbals are very similar
Correlation高表示這兩verbal很像
wait
等等的
ok so let's get back to this
好 那我們回到這個
Expression of this gene in Micro-A
Micro-A的這個基因的表現
you see these bright spots
你看到這些亮亮光亮點
first step
第一個步驟
you need to analyze the data
你要做資料的分析
You're going to do a lighten on this intensity
你要把這個強度做一個亮化
The lighting is very simple
那亮化都很簡單
That's what it's called how bright it is
那就是它的這個所謂的多亮
But the measurement of brightness is not enough
可是光亮亮度的測量不夠的
In fact, if you put this image
事實上在這個如果把這個image
transfer is the expression of the gene
轉称是這個基因的表現量
There are a lot of statistical
其中牽涉到的是很多的統計的
Application service
應用服
how it goes
它如何去
Because every different color has some bias
因為每一個不同的color 有些bias
There are also cases where this wavelength is different
也有情況不同的這個波長
it will have some of this deviation
它會有一些這個偏差
it is to correct
它是要correct
Then different just above this space
然後不同的剛剛這個空間上面
Different points may have some deviation
不同的點都可能有些偏差
These things have to be corrected
這些東西也要被矯正
Then some background noise
然後有些背景上面 noise
Then so this part belongs to the part of this image processing
然後所以這部分是屬於這個影像處理的部分
then more trouble
然後更麻煩了
this paragraph
這一段
after processing
處理完了之後
Usually all you have to do is
通常要做的就是
Action of Chip and Chip's Nong Ma Lai
Chip跟Chip的農馬來的Action
I am now in today's laboratory
就是我現在在今天實驗室
make a plane
造出一個機面來
After the next five minutes, another piece of machine noodles was created
下個五分鐘之後又造出一片機面
But it is in this film and the film
可是它在這個片跟片子
There is a different treatment of this
就有一種不同的這個處理
not saying different
不是說不同
the same way
同樣的處理方式
But the operation is always different
但是操作總是一片一片不一樣
Then the words inside
然後裡頭的話
There may be many, many factors
可能很多很多的因素
For example, sometimes your machine capacity is slightly different
比如說是有時候你這個機量稍微有點不一樣
poor temperature control
溫度控制不好
Or in this Processor
或者是在這個Processor的時候
you have to go through cleaning and so on
你都要經過清洗等等的
It is quite complicated Processor
是蠻複雜的Processor
Any step can go wrong
任何一個步驟都可能出錯
From then on we often see
那從此常常我們看到
This one looks very bright
這一片看起來就特別亮
That one looks less bright
那一片看起來比較不亮
what about these
那這些怎麼辦呢
These require statistical methods
這些就需要做過統計的方法
to do Normalization
去做Normalization
Now here comes the problem
那現在問題來了
everyone can do
大家都可以做
because
因為
There are too many statisticians
有太多太多的統計學家
In fact there are different teams
那事實上有不同的team
Each team's words are also quite famous
每個team的話也都是相當有名的
For example, my former colleague is now
比方說是以前我的同事現在是
Academician Wang Yongxiong
王永雄那個院士
Now at Stanford
現在在Stanford
They have a method called D-CHIP that must be used a lot
他們有一個叫D-CHIP的方法必用的非常多
The other word is
那另外一個的話是
Terry Speed's One
Terry Speed的一個
that
那個
Berger Professor of Statistics
Berger的統計教授
He has a very popular method
他有一套也是相當popular的方法
what about different methods
那不同的方法呢
Everyone uses a lot but
大家都用很多但是
The trouble is this result
麻煩就是這個result
the result is different
結果的話不同的
Message out
Message弄出來
tend to create
往往會造出
different and that difference is quite a difference
不同而且那個不同的話是相當大的不同
so what about this
所以這一點呢
there is no way
是沒有辦法的
The only suggestion is
那唯一的這個建議就是
You may need to use a little more method and find out his commonality
你也許需要用多一點的方法然後去找出他的共同性
Then
然後
hope at a different time
希望在不同的時候能夠
According to this experiment in the next step
根據下一步的這個 experiment
to determine which one would be better
去確定哪一個會比較好
The other concept I want to tell you is that
那另外一個觀念呢我要跟各位講的就是
Relative amount
相對量
We hope that in fact we want to say how many votes a certain gene has
我們希望事實上是希望說是某一個基因他有多少票先量
but this kind of thing
但是這種東西
he is so far unfeasible
他目前為止是不可行的
there is no way to do it like this
沒辦法有這樣子做
Now the only thing that can be done is
現在唯一能夠做到就是
The relative amount is the relative amount of this gene to that one.
相對量就是這個基因跟那個相對的量到底是多少
this thing
這個東西
can be detected
是能夠被測出來
What about after this preprocessing?
那經過這個前置的這個處理之後呢
What we got is this kind of out-of-string data is
我們得到的就是這樣子離串的這個數據就是
Here each row represents a gene
在這邊每一行代表一個基因
This is the gene. The first gene, the second gene, and the third gene are those light spots.
這是基因第一個基因第二個基因第三個基因就是那些光點得到的
Then
然後
listed like this
列這樣子的
First
第一
The first column is in this
第一列是在這個
The first piece, you need to make a
第一片,你在某一種情況之下需要做一個
The experiment obtained by the operation is this kind
經營的 experiment 得到就是這一種
You found a situation and got
你發現一個情況又得到了
It is a chip that represents a
就是一個 chip 代表一種
a condition
一個 condition
is the condition
就是經 condition
I use this below
我底下用這個
This cycle of filial mother bacteria to explain
孝母菌的這個周期來做解釋
This filial mother fungus in its lifetime
這個孝母菌在一生之中
he only does one thing
他只做一件事情
that is
就是
In copying one cell divides into two cells
在複製一個細胞分裂成兩個細胞
But this process is quite complicated
但是這個過程之中是相當複雜的
Filial piety mothers want to know
孝母學家就想知道說
at a certain stage
在某一個階段裡頭
Which genes are expressed
到底哪些基因被表現
Why can it be done from one place
為什麼從一個地方能夠進行到
which one next step
哪一個地下一個步驟
So there is something like this
所以就有這樣子的
gene expression data
基因的表現的資料
According to the data of such performance
根據這樣子的表現的資料
would have been very complicated
本來是非常複雜
But after the so-called
但是經過所謂的
So Cruster's method is to group genes with the same or similar expression
所以cruster的方法就是把基因的表現量相同的或類似的把它集在一起
Then you will see that if it is a certain piece of A, it becomes very similar
然後你就會看出來說是A某一塊的話就變成很像
And then this say this is the original part
然後這個比如說這是原來的部分
Then you take the same piece of a certain piece and enlarge it
然後你把某一塊的相同的把它放大
You can see it and see what its gene is doing
你看出來然後去看一下它的這個基因到底在幹什麼
For example, most of this area is rival zone
比如說這一塊大部分都是rival zone
It is the body of the translation of the gene that we just talked about
就是我們剛剛講到的就是翻譯的這個基因的翻譯的那些體
These things make the biologist happy
這些東西這個生物學家就很高興
He said that through these complex things that seem to have no clue
他說透過這些這個很複雜原來看起來沒有頭緒的東西
After you line up like this
經過你這樣子排排
Then it can be seen that the function of its gene is roughly the same
然後就可以看出來說它大致上它的這個基因的這個功能都一樣
So how does this work?
那這個是有怎麼樣子的作用
In case there are some genes in this piece
萬一在這一塊裡頭如果說有些基因
It also has a different notation
它還它的notation不一樣
I don't know, that is to say, he doesn't know his function yet.
不知道 就是說他還不知道他的功能
that is placed by this in the same
那被放在 被這個放在同一個
you can go and see
你就可以去看到
Then his function is probably the same as others already known
那他的功用大概是跟其他已經知道了一樣
So this is the most basic one, an application
所以這是最基本的一個 一個運用
What about this grouping method?
那這個分群方法呢
most important idea
最重要的觀念
that's the similarity
就是這個相似度
How is the similarity obtained?
那相似度是怎麼樣子得到的
Statistically above
統計上上面
is to use the so-called correlation coefficient
就是用所謂的這個相關系數
The correlation coefficient is used a lot in daily life
那相關系數在日程生活是用的非常多
like you
比方說是像你
height and weight
身高跟體重
We all know that there is a proportional relationship
大家知道成正比的關係
taller, heavier
身高越高 體重就越重
that's roughly the way it is
就是大致上就是這樣子
what about sometimes
那有時候呢
This correlation will become the inverse relationship
這個相關會成相反的關係
Let's say your test scores
比方說是你的考試成績
Questions that you answered incorrectly
跟你的答錯的題目
The more mistakes you make, the lower your score
錯的越多 你的分數越小
In other cases, less obvious
另外一些情況比較不明顯的
For example, age and speed
比方說是年齡跟速度
Age and speed are roughly the same as running five strings
年齡跟速度大概成一個跑五弦
when you were very young
你在很小的時候
Probably the older you are, the faster you run
大概是年齡越大 跑得越快
but when you grow old
可是你到老的時候
The older you get, you can't run
年齡越大 你跑不動
So the relationship is different
所以那關係的話就不一樣
Then the correlation coefficient is obtained according to a formula like this
那這相關系數是根據這樣子的一個公式得到
Then let me dance a little here to talk about some ceremonies
那我這邊稍微跳一下來講一些典禮
What about the correlation coefficient?
這個相關系數呢
It is rarely used by mathematicians, high teachers, etc.
被用的很少 數學家高師等等
But on the statistical series
但是在統計系列上面
Everyone admires this guy named Gelton
大家都推崇 就是這位叫Gelton的
He did a lot of interesting research during this period
他在這一段期間做很多很有趣的研究
Then he published an article
然後他發表一個文章
His article is typical low heredity
他的文章就是typical low heredity
Mate has a lot to do with biology
Mate跟生物上面很有關係
Then later KL Pearson promoted his method
然後後來KL Pearson把他方法推廣
The usual correlation we are talking about now is
我們現在講的通常correlation就是
It turned out to be Gelton
原來原是Gelton
Scientists at Gelton's time knew pretty much everything.
Gelton那時候的科學家差不多什麼都懂
Another explorer and Georgia, Mentor, etc.
又是一個探險家又是Georgia, Mentor,等等的
He's a Half-Carson from Darwin
他是達爾文的一個Half-Carson
so he's very interesting about the agenda
所以他對這個議程非常有趣
One of the most important jobs he did was regulatory analysis
他做的一個最重要的工作就是regrational analysis
He used the relationship between the elevation of the previous generation and the next generation
他用的是上一代跟下一代的升高之間的關係
He downloaded it one by one based on the information at the time
他根據當時的資料一比一比的載下來
Then it is very hard to draw this picture
然後很辛苦的就是畫這個圖
This diagram is the most successful part of empirical science
這個圖是經驗科學以頭最成功的一部分
He just depends on how much the rise, the rise of the father, and the rise of the children
他就光靠這些升高多少,父親的升高多少,子女的升高多少
appear, several times in this position
出現,在這個位置出現有幾次
Such a frequency graph to deduce that
這樣子一個頻率的圖去推出說
This Distribution
這個Distribution
It is a flower circle with the same probability of equal height
它等高的相同機率出現的是一個朵圓
Everyone is round
每個都是團朵圓
are all circles in the same direction
都是同樣一個方向的朵圓
According to this thing, it can make some mathematical inferences
根據這個東西它就可以做一些數學的推斷
Then add some normally distributed variables
然後再加上一些常態分布的變數
It can put the two-bit Normal Distribution
它就可以把二位的Normal Distribution
come out
出來
But this is a very important formula
但這個是一個相當重要的一個公式
Everyone knows that the normal distribution is that Cov is long
常態分布大家都知道就是它Cov就是長
So it looks like a Bell
所以它像一個Bell的樣子
more in the middle
中間比較多
relatively few aspects
方面比較少
Let's take a look at a very simple application
那這邊我們先來看一個很簡單的這個應用
Here are four genes
這邊舉的是有四個基因
Called MCM1, MCM2, MCM3, MCM4, MCM5, MCM7
叫做MCM1、MCM2、MCM3、MCM4、MCM5、MCM7
Let's not worry about what it's doing for now
這些我們暫時不要去管它在做什麼的
Let's use the graph of its gene expression to see
我們用它的基因的這個表現的樣的圖來看
look at this
你看這個
mcm6 and mcm5
mcm6跟mcm5
What about each of these two genes?
這兩個基因每一點呢
Indicates that each point is a different condition
表示每一點都是一個不同的condition
its performance
裡頭它的表現量
So here it means that when mcm
所以這邊呢表示的是說當mcm
when it was high
高的時候呢
When mcm6 is high, mcm7 is also high
mcm6高的時候mcm7也是高
when d is also d
當d的時候也是d
So it is positively correlated
所以它是有正相關
So mcm7 is with
所以mcm7是跟
mcm6 has a positive correlation with this one
mcm6都有正相關跟這個也有
5 are positively related to this
5有正相關這個
4 have a positive correlation
4有正相關
3 has a positive correlation, this correlation is slightly less
3有正相關這個相關性稍微少一點
what about this
那這個呢
Correlation is very weak
相關性是非常弱啦
hardly relevant
幾乎沒有相關
Then take a good look at these
那你好好的仔細看這些呢
you will find
你會發現
This mcm1 is very strange
這個mcm1是特別怪
How does mcm1 relate to everyone?
mcm1的話跟大家的關係呢
are very weak
都非常弱
The other relationships are stronger.
那其他的關係呢都是比較強
so what would you infer
所以你會推斷什麼
So 2 to 7, its functions on creatures should be more like
所以說2到7它的生物上面的功能應該是比較像
Then the function of MCA1 will be relatively poor
然後MCA1的功能會比較差
That's actually what it looks like
那事實上也是這個樣子
The role of this MCA2 is to replicate this chromosome
這個MCA2它的作用它是在這個染色體的複製上
It helps in the replication of chromosomes
它是幫忙做染色體的複製
This MCA1 it is a transcription factor
這個MCA1它是一個transcription factor
is the transferred factor
就是轉入的因子
It is bind in front of this gene
它是bind在這個基因的前面
promoting
在促進
So the two functions are completely different
所以兩個功能是完全不一樣
So just relying on this simple statistic
所以光靠這個簡單的統計量
You can make an inference like this
你就可以做這樣子的一個推斷
The one I'm going to talk about next is more advanced than similarity
我底下要講的一個是比相似度更高級
higher level
更高一層次的
Then this is quite surprising
那這個是相當surprising的
What about this concept?
這個觀念呢
it was me in 2002
是我在2002年
I just started jumping into this time
我剛開始跳入這個時候
I find
我發現
At that time a lot of people have done a lot of things
那時候很多人已經做很多東西
like this Crossing
像這個Crossing
everyone did
大家都做了
then i was thinking
那我在想
what am i doing here
那我進來幹什麼
Is there anyone who already knows
是不是有什麼人家都已經會
Everyone can use computer
computer大家都會用
then i will think about some
那我就想一些
Is there still fish in the meat net?
是不是還有肉網之魚
There are some ideas
還有一些觀念上面
Everyone hasn't thought of it yet
大家還沒想到的
but don't be too responsible
但是不要太負責
because you talk to the school of life
因為你跟生活學校談東西
Or what, you talked too complicated all at once
還是怎麼樣你一下子談得太複雜
they can't accept
他們沒辦法接受
Then there will be some in the middle
那就中間就會有一些
There are some gaps
有一些Gap
Then I hope to find a very simple solution
那我希望弄一個很簡單的辦法
but there's still something you can do
但是還有一些東西可以做
Let everyone unexpected at the same time
讓大家想不到的同時
Is it possible to convince the school of life that
是不是能夠說服生活學校這個
also useful
也有用
Then this article is here
那這一篇在這個
that PNS
那個PNS
that is
就是
The PNS above in 2002
上面2002年的PNS
post below
下面發表
then i
那我
Because just now the dean and the vice dean also mentioned that I was born in the Department of Mathematics
因為剛剛院長 副院長也提到我是數學系出生的
in college
大學的時候
What we often ask in mathematics is a logical relationship
數學上面我們常常問的是一個邏輯上面的關係
if a then b
if a then b
if a holds
如果a成立的話
This b is established if this is a true statement
這b成立 如果說這是一個對的敘述
Then its counter-narrative may not be correct
那它的反敘述不見得對
If b is right, you may not be right about a
如果說是b是對的話 你不見得a會對
This is a logically important concept
這是一個邏輯上面很重要的觀念
So ask a question like this
所以就問一個這樣子的問題
Just now we know that your two genes have a high degree of similarity
就是剛剛我們知道說是你兩個基因它的相似度很高
Then we biologists focus on its biological function
那我們生物學家就團到 它的生物上的功能
will be more or less the same
都會大致上一樣
So one question I ask is
那我問的一個問題就是說
If two genes are related
如果說是兩個基因它關係
is very similar
是很像
ok that ok
好 那 ok
you two on this creature
你兩個這個生物上面
it's related to genes that act a lot like
它有關係它的作用很像的基因
it's this expression it's the expression
它的這個expression 它是表現量
Is the degree of belief very high?
相信的程度是不是很高
i repeat
我再重複一次
What we saw earlier is
在前面我們看到的是
If it is two genes, its expression is above
如果說是兩個基因它的表現量上面
its similarity is high
它的相似的程度很高
Biologists will accept that it functions above
生物學家會接受說是它的功能上面
There is a fair chance it will be the same
有相當大的可能性它會是相同的
or similar
或是類似的
What we are now asking is the opposite
我們現在要問的是相反的
That is, two genes are related in the same way.
就是兩個基因它是同樣關係的
participating in the same function
參加同樣功能的
It's on this gene expression
它在這個基因表現上面
Will it be that there is often a great degree of similarity
會不會是有往往都是有很大的相似程度
that answer is wrong
那答案是不對的
It's because of our genes
就是因為我們這個基因裡頭
its regulation
它的調控
it's too complicated
實在太複雜了
My first Ns is of course that micro-ray is too noisy
我第一個Ns當然就是micro-ray太noise
but noise is another matter
不過noise是另外一回事
Because of the regulation of your gene
因為你這個基因的調控
is a very complex structure
是非常複雜的一個結構
So while two genes are participating in the same industry
所以雖然兩個基因是在參與同業的工作
Because there are many external factors interfering there
因為有很多外在的因子在那邊干擾
so your words won't be consistent
所以你表現出來的話不會一致
Here are some reasons for the list
這邊就是list的一些原因
do i think i'll just skip this part
難道我想這一部分我就把它跳過去
don't talk about it
不去談它
in fact
事實上
on a further molecular level
在更進一步的分子角度上面
There is also a phenomenon
也有一種現象
I'm here to say quickly
我這邊很快的說
That is, your genes fall into the so-called Histone
就是你的基因是落在所謂的Histone
the so-called main protein
所謂主蛋白上面
you are some chromosomes
你是一些染色體
Then
然後
So it by itself suppresses the expression of this gene
所以它本身會抑制這個基因的表現
You need to open this thing first
你要把這個東西先打開來
make it not wrapped in
讓它不包在
You can have genetic expression
你才能夠有基因表現
So there's a gene here
所以在這邊有一種基因
There is a transcription factor
有一種transcription factor
it works weird
它的作用很怪
even if it is a repressor
它即使是一個repressor
is also an activator
也是一個activator
what is repressor
repressor是什麼
its turn factor
它的轉路因子
it suppresses gene expression
它是來壓制基因表現量
activator is just the opposite
activator是剛好相反
But in some cases it can do both
可是有些的話它兩個都可以做
The reason why it can do both
它之所以會有兩個都可以做
It turns out that there are other factors at work
原來是因為有其他的因子在干
This example is a pretend finite number
這個例子是一個假裝限數
This pretends to limit this Harm to do its job
這個假裝限數這個Harm做它的調工
It has a structure without pretending to be limited
沒有假裝限數的時候它有一種結構
There are pretending to limit the number of its structures to change
有假裝限數它結構去改變
so we often say
所以我們常常說
a certain turn factor
某一個這個轉路因子
It is positively regulated
它是有正向的調控
a turn factor
某一個轉路因子
attached regulation
有附向的調控
This way of speaking is too five paragraphs
這樣子講法太過五段
Some of these regulators
有些這個調供因子
There are forward and reverse
那正向反向都有
that controls whether it is forward or bidirectional
那控制它是正向或兩向
are some other extrinsic factors
是一些其他外在因子
Now here comes the problem
那現在問題來了
these extrinsic factors
就是這些外在因子
how do we know
我們怎麼知道呢
the biologist
那生物學家
he because
他因為
many things are sprouting
很多東西都在萌芽
limited knowledge
所知有限
so he doesn't know
所以他也不知道
Then ask our ruler
那問我們這個統治學家
more laymen
更是外行
how do you know
怎麼知道
you don't know of course i don't know
你不知道我當然不知道
then i
那我
but i just told you
但是我剛跟各位講說
what about statisticians
統計學家還是怎麼樣
something mathematicians are not afraid of
數學家們不怕的東西
is that we can make some assumptions
就是我們可以做一些假設
we want to start from position
我們要從位置
there is something from the chair
有從椅子的東西
or part chair
或是部分椅子
we go to test the location of things
我們去催測位置的東西
made some models
做過一些模型上面
So let's make an adult's assumption here
所以這邊去做一個大人的假設說
OK, if the gene
OK 如果說這個基因
with the things it regulates
跟這個它調控的東西
in a certain state
在某一種狀態之下
it has positive
它有正向的
It is a
它是一個
positive transfer
正向的調供
then in another state
然後在另外一個狀態之下
it has a reverse feed
它有反向的調供
But I control this turn
但是我這個調控這個轉
The forward or reverse of these timbres
這個正向或反向的這些音質
I have no idea
我不知道
But I make an assumption
但是我做一個假設
Say this, these sound quality, or this state
說這個這些音質或是這個狀態
will be on a certain pitch
是會在某一個基音上面
will be shown
會被表現出來
it's just an assumption
這只是一個假設
So in this different this
所以在這個不同的這個
For example, when Hormono
比如說荷爾門多的時候
This State 1
這個State 1
its fundamental tone it doesn't show
它這個基音它沒有表現
But when there is less hormonal
但是荷爾門少的時候
This pitch is more than expressed
這個基音就比表現出來了
then i can
那我就可以
There is a hypothesis like this
有這樣子一個假設
I don't need to know that it's hormonal that affects this
我不需要知道說是影響這個是荷爾門
I just need to know that it affects it
我只要知道說是影響它的
Just a certain pitch
是某一個基音就可以了
Although this thing is the most important
雖然這個東西是最主要
but its performance
但是它的表現
So I make an assumption like this
所以我就做這樣子的一個假設
So through a situation like this
所以透過這樣子的一個情況
In addition to saying that the pitch and its
除了說這個基音跟它的這個
This is a transfer sound quality
這是一個轉入音質
This is the pitch of its regulation
這是它的調控的基音
It is sometimes a positive regulation
它有時候是正向調控
negative regulation
也是負向調控
but you not only
但是你不只
Knowing this is true, you would think
就知道這個真的情況你會認為
he doesn't matter
他沒有關係
But if you say that through this third gene
但是你如果說是透過這個第三個基因
When your third gene doesn't express
當你這個第三個基因他沒有表現的時候
all green
都是綠的
just these times
就是只有這些時候
If it's red, that's all
如果說是紅的就這些
So it's a very simple concept
所以這是一個很簡單的一個觀念
that's how it behaves
就是這樣子表現出來
But it's so dark here that it's us
但是這裡頭天色到就是我們
can't be the same
不能跟以前一樣
Previously it was only necessary to link two genes to see how similar they were
以前只要聯繫兩個基因看它的相似程度
That now turns into studying three genes
那現在就變成要研究三個基因
That's X, Y, Z
就是X、Y、Z
that's more complicated
那就更複雜了
What is the level of complexity?
複雜程度是怎麼樣子呢?
we are doing
我們在做
Like the example just now, when making filial mother fungus
像剛剛例子是在做孝母菌的時候
Probably around 6,000 genes
大概也差不多六千個基因左右
Of the 6,000 genes you have to take three
六千個基因你要取三
thirty eight
三十八
This is 5878
這個是5878
Counting is 33.8 triplets of point B
算一下是33.8個B點的triplet
That's too much
那這量實在太大了
If the quantity is too large
這樣子量太大的話
I can't say a triplet
我就沒辦法說一個triplet
Just use the priest method just now to look at his relationship
就用剛剛的那個牧師法去看他的關係
I must
我一定要
Provide a statistic for the computer to calculate
提供一個統計量讓computer去算
What about the amount?
那這個量呢
How did you recruit them?
到底是怎麼樣子的招出來呢
I inferred from some of these mathematical statistics
我就透過一些這個數理統計上面推論
I'm sorry about this
這個很抱歉
i'm just here
我只是在這邊
It's just like show off
只是等於是show off一下
Just a reference
參考參考就好
So after some statistics, some definitions above, etc.
所以經過一番統計上面的一些定義等等
found that under such circumstances
發現這種情況之下
there is a nice formula
有一個很好的公式
You can use this to calculate this
可以拿來這個計算這個
The formula is simply
這個公式很簡單就是
x1 y1 z1
x1 y1 z1
cover up
x2 y2 z2
multiply up add up
乘起來加起來
What is x1 y1 z1 x2 y2 z2
那x1 y1 z1 x2 y2 z2是什麼
That is, the three genes are different
就是三個基因在不同
Performance under condition
condition之下的表現量
so very simple
所以非常簡單
in a certain state
在某一種狀態之下
how much the first gene is expressed
第一個基因的表現多少
how much the second gene is expressed
第二個基因表現多少
how much the first three genes express
第一個三個基因表現多少
just ride it up
把它乘起來就好
everyone will be punished
大家都會做懲罰
in the second case
在第二個情況之下
add it up too
也把它加起來
So all your data adds up like this
所以你所有的資料就這樣子加起來
This is my consideration
這個就是我的這個顧及量
Then this example is called liquid association
那這個顧例叫做liquid association
Liquid association is a relatively abstract concept
liquid association的話是一個比較抽象的一個觀念
It is mainly used to describe
它是主要是拿來描述說
this
這個
correlation
correlation這相關相
will be like
會像
Liquids flow like water
液態一樣會像水一樣會流動
Sometimes it's positive, sometimes it's negative
有時候會變正有時候會變負
there will be this fluttering
會有這種飄動的
image
形象
What about a formula like this?
那這樣子的一個公式呢
In fact, it is equivalent to a
其實呢是等於是一個
Fissure yes correlation a generalization
fissure yes的correlation一個推廣
Fissure i fissure is arguably the most famous statistician in the world
fissure i fissure是可以說世界上公認最有名的這個統計學家
That
那
Yes, it is also looking for a very important statistician
yes呢也是找一個很重要的統計學家
then they
那他們
When doing this correlation before, he didn’t follow the same route as Pearlson
以前在做這個correlation的時候他不走這個pearlson那一套路線
he is
他是
Do say I just put this first each
做說我只要先把這個每一個
Statistics first make it a normal score transformation first normalize it
統計量先把它做一個normal score transformation先把它常態化
then you
然後你
After normalizing it
把它常態化之後呢
I want to calculate his two correlation is very simple
我要算他兩個correlation就很簡單
It's fine if the two inherit each other.
兩個相承 出起來就好了
this is their method
這是他們的方法
This method has its benefits
這個方法有它的好處
it for those
它對那些
The so-called Outline
所謂的Outline
Sometimes the data is messy
有些時候資料很亂
some words jump especially big
有些某些字跳得特別大
This method will not be so Sensitive
這個方法就不會那麼Sensitive
can limit
可以 limits
my method
我這個方法就
almost equal to this replica of it
幾乎等於它的這個翻版
add an extra gene
多加一個基因
But the math behind it is completely different.
不過 背後用到的數學原理是完全不一樣的
so that's
所以那就是
I'll do a little math for the benefit
我會做一點數學的好處
So here is the Normal distribution
所以這邊就講到這個Normal distribution
how did it work
到底是怎麼做的
back to this
回到這個
This example of filial mother
孝母菌的這個例子
let me tell you one
我來講一個
only one application
唯一的一個應用
Because what I said today is that there are several applications left
因為我今天的話是剩下好幾個應用
But maybe I'm not here because of time
但是可能時間的關係我就不在這
keep talking about this app
一直講這個應用
this application
這個應用
looks very complicated
看起來非常複雜
actually
其實
you know other results
你知道其他的結果
The secret is actually quite simple
其中奧妙其實是蠻簡單的
This is a
這是一個
path of chemical reaction
化學反應的路徑
Its main purpose is to illuminate the Aquini
它的最主要目的是要照這個阿基尼
This Aquini is crystal dark acid
這個阿基尼就是晶暗酸
It is a series of chemical reactions
它是經過一連串的化學反應
Every chemical reaction involves an enzyme
每一個化學反應都有牽涉到一個酵素
Its original source is from ancient times
它最初的源頭是從古特美
Gutmey is blessing dark acid
古特美就是福暗酸
Through this ARG2 enzyme
經過這個 ARG2 的酵素
ARG2 is this synthetic beauty
ARG2 就是這個合成美
And then make this called Osli Bird Dark Sour
然後再做成這個叫做奧斯里鳥暗酸
and then after here
然後到這邊之後
Its chemical reaction is going this way
它這個化學反應是往這邊走的
If you come here, the next step is to become this Psytrillion
過來的話下一步要變成這個 Psytrillion
is hanging dark acid
就是掛暗酸
Then wait until the end to get Crystal Dark Acid
然後等等最後才得到晶暗酸
When your crystal dark acid if too much
當你的晶暗酸如果太多的時候
it will be broken down again
它又會被分解掉
This breaks down into
這個分解成
back to this bird dark sour
回到這個鳥暗酸
So this is a cycle
所以這就是一個cycle
This is quite effective
這個是相當作用的
Because this has uria cycle
因為這有uria cycle
word from here
從這邊的話
After this crystal dark acid is decomposed
從這個晶暗酸被分解了之後
will run deep in this uria
就會跑得深這個uria
So what about the loop
所以這個循環呢
Although on filial mother fungi
雖然是在孝母菌上有
The same is true for the human body and the kidneys
在人體、腎臟什麼也是同樣
is a very important mechanism
是一個很重要的機制
Then if you look at a picture like this
那你去看這樣子一個圖的話
look at these chemical reactions
你看這些化學反應
how do i know
我做統計怎麼知道
But this is very certain
但是這個是非常有確定
imagine these chemical reactions
想像這些化學反應
In fact, it is like a string of processing factories.
其實就是像一串的加工廠一樣
so stuff comes in
所以東西進來
I just parse it
我就把它parsage就好了
So let's say
所以比方說是
when you want to take this thing
你要照這個東西的時候
this thing must have
這個東西一定要有
So the more this thing
所以這個東西越多的話
I will show more of this thing
就照出越多這個東西來
But my goal is to follow this
但是我目標是要照這個
So if say this CR2
所以如果說這個CR2
nuclease
核酸酶
have something
有東西
also expressed a lot of words
也被表現出來很多的話
Then this Ostiny thing
那這個Ostiny這個東西
Will it be broken down immediately?
是不是馬上就會被分解掉
Then it would be wrong to do false work for nothing.
那就白做虛工了就不對了
So you'd guess that yes
所以你會推測說是
When ARG2 it expresses high
當ARG2它表現量高的時候
When the synthetic surface is high
這個合成面高的時候
this thing shouldn't exist
這個東西就不應該存在
It should express less
它應該表現量少
Otherwise, you just go in
要不然的話你這個一進去
It will be digested immediately, and it will be a waste of work
馬上就消化了就白做虛工了
So you would speculate that the relationship between these two
所以你會推測說是這兩個的關係
should be related
應該是互相關的關係
This is higher and this is lower
這個越高這個越低
Then let's see if Data looks like this
那我們看一下Data是不是這樣子
Sorry, this jumps a few pages first
對不起這個先跳幾頁
I'll come back to this later
等一下還會回過頭來講這個
Let's look at Data first
我們先看一下Data
This data is for everyone not to look at these two lines
這個Data是請大家先不要去看這兩條線
Also don't look at these red dots or different colors
也不要看這些紅點還是不同的顏色
Every point is a data point
每一點就是一個資料點
This information is from what we just talked about
這個資料是從我們剛剛講到
The information on Sale Cycle
Sale Cycle的那個資料
Exactly the same but I use it to study different things
完全一模一樣不過我拿來研究不同的東西
You said oh oh, check to see if there is anything related
你説喔喔你看一下到底有沒有相關
It cannot be positively correlated without correlation
沒有相關它不可能是正相關
If it is positively correlated, it should look like this
正相關的話它應該是這樣子一坨
Direct phase is not reverse
正相也不是反向
Not reverse is no correlation
不是反向是沒有相關性
that's not relevant
那沒有相關性
Then we just speculated that
那我們剛剛又推測說
Just now I speculated that it was these two, if so
剛剛又推測說是這兩個如果說是這樣
Cell needs RNG saying these two should have a negative correlation
細胞需要RNG說這兩個應該有負相關的相關性
why didn't that
為什麼那沒有呢
Then I said ok then it's okay
那我說OK那這沒關係
Then maybe if the cells disappear forever, it will be RNG
那也許細胞不見的永遠就RNG
Not called RGN
不叫RGN
it maybe sometimes it doesn't need
它也許有些時候它不需要
how do i know
那我怎麼知道呢
How do I know when it's needed and when it's not
我怎麼知道它什麼時候要什麼時候不需要
Then I will use this liquid manual to learn how to use it
那我就用這個liquid的手學用方法
My hypothesis is that maybe at some point it will
我的假設就是說也許在有些時候它要
maybe it doesn't
也許是它不要
what time does it want
它要的時候是什麼時候呢
Maybe some of the elite will be shown when it wants to
它要的時候也許某些精英會被表現出來
which elites
哪些精英呢
how could I know
我怎麼知道
I don't know it's okay
我不知道沒關係
find one by one
一個一個去找
so how do i find it
所以我怎麼找呢
this is me
我就是這個
I take this thing as x
我把這個東西當成x
This thing is regarded as y, so there is no
這個東西當成y 那它中間沒有
without that
沒有那個
correlation so it is
correlation 所以就是
To count this liquid association
去算這個liquid association
For each gene, there are about 6,000 genes in total, and each one is counted, so the basic calculation is not too big
對於每一個基因總共有6000個基因左右 每一個都去算 所以基算還不算大
then arrange it
然後把它排列
and then went to see its largest and found
然後去看它最大的 然後結果發現
The eighth largest here is the small
第八大的這邊是小
this
這個
negative biggest
負的最大的
Find this gene as soon as you look for it, that's good because there are 6,000 genes
一找就找到這個基因 那這個很好 因為6000個基因裡頭
The eighth is around here
第八位就是在這附近
so this
所以這個
It can be said that it was hit
可以說是中了
hit
中到了
Not only that
其實不只那樣子
Here it is, if you look more closely
在這邊呢 從更仔細去看的話
But you can see that when the CPA is
你卻可以看出來說是當這個CPA是
when performance is high
表現量高的時候
it has a negative correlation
它具有負相關
The negative correlation we want is when
我們要的負相關是當
CPA is when performance is high
CPA是表現量高的時候
When the CPA performance is small it is
當CPA表現量小的時候它是
multiply positive correlation
乘正相關
Is this relationship reasonable?
那這個關係呢到底合不合理
let's look back
我們再回過頭來看
What does it mean when this gene is expressed high?
當這個基因如果表現高的時候代表什麼意思呢
If this thing is high, it can take this Gutmin
這個東西一高的話它可以把這個Gutmin
Decomposition then yields this
分解然後就產生這個
This metabolite of Carbomile phosphate
Carbomile phosphate的這個代謝物
What about this metabolite?
這個代謝物呢
Can Oscling with this
可以跟這個Oscling
Through this ARG this synthesis
透過這個ARG這個合成
to synthesize this
去合成這個
so
所以
When this you do RG0
當這個你要做RG0的時候
Right and wrong need not only Oscling
是非需要不只需要Oscling
At the same time you also need this Carbomile
同時你也需要這個Carbomile
Then you need Carbomile
那你需要Carbomile這個東西
It's about to come out. If you don't have this synthesis, you won't have it.
就要出來你沒有這個合成沒的話就沒有
so
所以
My explanation is that when the composition does not show
我的解釋就是說是當這個合成沒有表現
It will represent that the cell needs RG0
就會代表細胞需要RG0
When the cell needs RG0
在細胞需要RG0的時候
ARG2 is just negatively correlated with CR2
ARG2跟CR2就剛好成負相關
So this is completely represented by our picture
所以這個就是完全由我們這一張圖表現出來
Another situation is when CR2 does not perform
另外一種情況就是說當CR2沒有表現的時候
It happens to be DR's WareRound
剛好是DR的WareRound
just another situation
就是另外一種情況
That is, when there is no here, it means that there is no need here
就是當這邊沒有的時候表示這裡都不需要
those are the times when you don't need it
那是一些不需要的時候
In that case, it means that the cell
那種情況就表示說是細胞裡頭
Maybe this arginic acid is too much
可能這個精安酸太多了
If there is too much arginic acid, it will break down
精安酸太多的話它就是要分解
So when you want to decompose this thing should show
所以當你要分解的時候這個東西要表現出來
So when you are still tall
所以當你這個還有高的時候
If your stuff is not high
你這個東西如果說是不高的話
that's bad
那不好了
It will also be forced on this may produce more
它也會被force上這個說不定就產生更多了
So the best solution is when this high
所以最好的解決辦法就是當這高的時候
The god you produce is digested immediately
你產生出來的阿神馬上就被消化掉
broken down
被分解掉
Use CR2 performance to decompose it
用CR2表現量高去把它分解
So this is a rather subtle
所以這個是一個相當微妙的
right here
就是在這個
The enzymes in the shells that we often eat
我們常常吃的這個貝殼的這個酵素裡頭
Inside a little angry bag
一個小小生氣包裡頭
by the expression of this gene
靠著這個基因的表現
complicated inside
里頭複複雜雜
6000 genes inside
6000個基因裡頭
Let's watch these
我們就觀看這幾顆
It's all in this picture
完全就表現在這一張圖上面
Then you look out and see it's totally irrelevant
那你出眼看它是完全沒有相關的
But you should use statistical methods well
但是你好好的去用統計的方法
go
去
From what is already known to infer some positions
由現已經知道去推測一些位置的
Can find a quite reasonable explanation
居然可以找出一個相當合理的解釋
Then this method can be used a lot
那這個方法的話可以用了很多
means you have two genes
就是說你有兩個基因
I'm going to find a third gene that regulates these two
我去找第三個基因來調控這兩個
there is a way
這是有方法
That can also be said in reverse
那也可以反過來講
I one I can start with a gene
我一個我可以由一個基因開始
See which genes it can regulate
看它可以調控哪些基因
wait
等等的
Then this method can also be extended to
那這個方法也可以發展推廣到
more genes above
更多的基因上面
That uses some other math
那用到的又是另外一些數學
Are these just for reference?
這些是不是參考參考就好了
that's in this
那在這個
ah early words
啊早期的話
ah for publication
啊為了發表
During the paper period, I went to find some
paper期間我就去找一些在人
this on the gene
基因上面的這個
Information
資料啊
and found
然後發現
there is a group
有一組
The information can be brought here
資料可以拿來這個
do some of this
做一些這個
Ah, the research on human genes
啊人體的基因上面的這個研究
According to that information
我根據那個資料呢
ah
啊
At that time, for some reason
那時候據某種原因的話
Special interest in dementia
對老年癡呆症特別有興趣
then read some books
那就去看了一些書
then just
然後就啊
ah see some of this
啊看到一些這個
major gene
主要的這個基因
that is
就是
ah on top of this
啊在最重要的這個
I just saw some black ones that are called
剛剛看到一些黑黑的那一塊就是這個叫做
amino acid beta peptide
aminoid beta peptide
this thing is made of
這個東西呢是由
a large protein
一個大的 protein
After two of this chemical this
經過兩個這個化學的這個
Enzyme changes, this
酵素的變化啊這個
7. I just feel that I can use the lump at the bottom to compare
7啦就是覺得用底下這一坨比較
want
要
show it
表現的出來
That's the big one
就是原來這一個大大個
This red part is
這紅的這一部分是
This is what caused your brain age
是這個造成你這個腦齡
eat the most important ingredient
吃到最主要的一個成分
Then this ingredient needs to be cut by two enzymes
那這個成分是要經過兩個酵素去切
Then one by one
然後一個一刀呢
just on the left
就是在左邊
Then a knife is on the right
然後一刀是在右邊
Those two are two different enzymes
那這兩個是兩種不同的酵素
good
好
That
那
Then the APP’s role in general physiology
那這個APP它在一般的生理上面的作用
Actually it's not clear
其實是不太清楚了
Then in 2001
那在這個2001年的時候
it was me just then
就是我剛剛那時候
Really like this liquid phone
真的對這個liquid的手機
When I first started researching
剛開始研究的時候
This paper just came out
這一篇論文剛好出來
Then what
然後呢
it's taken from some chemistry experiments
它就作為從一些化學實驗
It found this APP?
它發現這個APP呢
with these two proteins
跟這兩個 protein
were caught together at the same time
同時被一起抓出來
They use a
它們是用一種
a kind of that
一種那個
It's like saying you're going to commit a crime first.
等於說要先行犯了一樣
he opened the cell
他把細胞打開了
then make some discoveries
然後做一些發現
found this thing combined with him
發現這個東西跟他結合在一起
This thing is combined with him
這個東西跟他結合在一起
if that thing is put together
那東西如果結合在一起的話
I would deduce that he should have
我會推斷他應該有
Fang Xiong should have related
那個方雄上面應該會有相關
Fangxiong related words
那方雄相關的話
on the expression of this gene
在這個基因表現上面
not necessarily relevant
不見得有相關
because i this is my original subject
因為我這是我最初的主題
then he is
那他的確是
Correlation is indeed very little
相關性的確是很少
His correlation is very little
他的correlation非常少
so i say
所以我說
Then this is EH maybe use liquid
那這是EH說不定用liquid
The method learned
所學習的辦法
So I put this APP
所以我就把這個APP
When X and Y are regarded as one of them
當X、Y當成其中的一個
Then
然後
Here is the human body
這邊是人體的
So this whole gold probably
所以這個整個金大概
At that time their gold piece
那時候他們的這個金片
technology limitation
技術的limitation
probably made almost ten thousand
大概弄得差不多將近一萬個
So just the same job
所以就同樣的一個工作
one to find those related
一去找那些相關的
first to find this
第一找到這個
PSEN
PSEN
this is the code
這是code
this
這個
oops , a little too fast
哎呀,是不是太快了一點
you want to go back
你要回到
Sorry, one of them may have been skipped
抱歉,可能有一張有跳掉
OK, that one dropped in the second place
OK,那個是在第二位就掉了
That is to say, simply explain
也就是說簡單講解
this
這個
what about my result
我的結果呢
It's in that very high ranking
就是在那個很高的這個順位裡頭
just found this
就是找到這個
it has related this
它有相關的這個
PSAN
PSAN
then this thing is
那這個東西是
Gama Security
Gama Security
what about the other one
那另外一個呢
same, good
也是一樣,很好
This X, that's another
這個X,那是另外一個
was caught at the same time as it
跟它有同時被抓到的
then go to see
然後去看
The result you see is this
看到的結果呢是這個
Base 2, that is
Base 2,那就是
Veta Side's APP
Veta Side的APP
Cricked Entire
Cricked Entire
Simple explanation, just use this method
簡單講解,就是用這個方法呢
it's ingenious
就是很巧妙的
That is, in 10,000 manager heads
就是在一萬個經理頭
Use this XY to find
用這個XY去找
I found out that it happened to be these two audio loaders.
找出來就是剛好這兩個音載
Its score is very high
它的這個score都非常高
And then down here is an app
然後底下來這是一個應用
That's because there is a doctor
那因為有一個博士
I know that at UCL
我認識說在UCL
this postdoc
這一個博士後
He is from Human Genetic
他是從Human Genetic
he sees these results
他看到這些結果
he is very interested
他就很有興趣
So I found his instructor
所以就找了他的這個指導老師
Come and discuss with me
一起過來跟我做探討
Then his team is right about this
那他那個team是對這個
Multiple Sclerosis
Multiple Sclerosis
polymorphism
就是多發性的印化症
very interested
非常有興趣
the european white
那歐洲人白人
This specifies a lot
這個指定非常多
Then it's a Neuron's this
那它是一個Neuron的這個
Simply put, the immune system
就是簡單講解就是免疫系統
this cell that is attacking this nerve
在攻擊這個神經的這個細胞
put this outside this
把這個外面的這個
The Mining of the students
學員的這個Mining
persecuted it
把它迫害掉了
so he starts this
所以他就開始這個
there are some scars coming out
有一些scar出來
Then it recurs after a while
然後過一陣子又會復發
that's usually looking for the gene
那通常在找這個基因
Generally, it is the route of Genovice
一般都是做Genovice的路線
That is, where do you go to see people doing some Genovice
就是你去看哪些地方有人做一些Genovice
at that time i was
那時候我就是
Learning while doing Liquid
正在做Liquid的時候學習
So what is used is a quite different method from ordinary people.
所以用到的是一個相當一般人不一樣的辦法
What was used at that time was
那時候用的東西是
This data is completely Geneexpression data
這個data是完全是Genexpression data
Not this marker data
不是這個marker data
gene expression data
Genexpression data
At the same time, these Geneexpression data
同時這些Genexpression的資料
It has nothing to do with this Multiple Sclerosis
跟這個Multiple Sclerosis完全沒有關係
this one is
這個其中一個是
researching this
專門在研究這個
i-Zen is different from i-C8
i-Zen的不同的i-C8的
Then additionally these data are
然後另外這些資料是
looking at the different organs of the body
在看看說是身體的各種不同器官
expression of these genes
這些基因的表現
how to be different
要怎麼樣的不同
These data are completely unrelated to Multiple
這些跟Multiple是完全沒有相關的那些資料
And what about the MVP?
然後這個MVP呢
is a gene
是一個基因
it is
它是
It is the cell in this Mining
它在這個Mining就是細胞
In the outer layer of nerve cells, there are many manifestations
神經細胞的外層裡頭表現非常多
So it's a very important Proton
所以它是一個非常重要的Proton
So take it as X
所以把它拿來當X
what is Y
Y是什麼
Y is provided by our collaborators
Y是我們的合作者提供的
They were very interested in this gene at the time
他們那時候對這個基因非常感興趣
Because they are this difficult TIN
因為他們這是這個分難的TIN
where he found
他在那邊發現
After some genetics above this Typing
經過一些遺傳上面的這個Typing
It was found that this gene is likely to be related to this Multiple Sclerosis
發現這個基因很可能會跟這個Multiple Sclerosis有關
So he just provided the gene
所以他就是提供了這個基因
and this gene
還有這個基因
Then the rest is our bioinformatics method
然後剩下來就是我們這個生物資訊的方法
find these information
去找這些資料
Then some with Liquid's hands
然後用Liquid的手一些
Then I found this gene in the second place early in the morning
然後一早就找到這個基因排名在第二順位
Then use this gene
然後用這個基因
And do liquid association with this gene
又跟這個基因做liquid association
is xy
就是xy
find it related
找它相關
Find a lot more
又找出一大堆來
According to different data
根據不同的data
This way you get a table
這樣子就得到一張表
Most importantly, this gene
最重要的是這個基因
the word of the gene
這個基因的話
Our collaborator is very interested
我們的這個collaborator很有興趣
because they were doing a
因為他們那時候正在做一個
Research
研究
The gene itself is interesting
這個基因本身就是很有趣
Because it is Glutamate
因為它是Glutamate
Glutamate is a
Glutamate是一個
neurotransmitter
neurotransmitter
it's very important
它非常重要
This gene is specialized in this neurotransmitter
這個基因是專門在這個neurotransmitter
A very important thing that is sent from the inside of the cell to the outside
從細胞裡面送到外面的一個很重要的
this
這個
protein
蛋白質
OK this
OK這個
because
因為
sorry this is barely watchable
對不起這個幾乎不能看
Because I'm using MaconTosh
因為我用的是MaconTosh
Every time you turn to this, it turns like this
你轉到這個每次都是轉成這個樣子
of course it doesn't matter
當然沒關係
These incomprehensible things
這一頭這些看不懂的東西
In fact, it was my team who did Gino typing
其實是我那個team他去做Gino typing
found this
發現這個
there is an association
是有 association
But what?
可是呢
The problem is because they use too little data
問題是因為他們用的 data 太少了
Only about 300
大概只有 300 個
So we are publish wanting to publish
所以我們是 publish 想要 publish
So referee told us to do more
所以 referee 叫我們多做一點
That
那
Because of this personnel, resources are limited
因為這個人員啊 資源有限
so we didn't go ahead
所以我們沒有繼續做
But what?
不過呢
It happens to be a gift that fell from the sky
剛好是可以說是天上掉下一個禮物
just in
就是在
In 2007
2007 年的時候吧
在 New England Journal of Medicine
在 New England Journal of Medicine
There is an article like this
出現了這樣子一個文章
this is a very large
這是一個非常大型的這個
generalized study
generalized study
he used
他用的
There are about 12,360 subjects
大概有 12,360 個 subject
There are 609 family to you etc.
有 609 個 family to you 等等的
very large and is
非常大型的 而且是
Cross-centre and transnational cooperation
跨centre 跨國的合作
They use this generalized association method
他們用這個 generalized association 的辦法
Find the two most important experiences
找到最重要的兩個經驗
One is IL-2R and the other is IL-7
一個是 IL-2R 另外一個是 IL-7
ah
啊
Then I see iOS 11
那我看到iOS 11
This thing seems familiar
這個東西好像似曾相識
I'll go back and have a look
那我就回去看一下
Hey, if you look at it, this iOS 11A you look at here
欸 看的話這個iOS 11A 你看在這邊
So from this totally unrelated genics
所以在從這個完全不相關的這個genics
Franchon data
Franchon data
Through this and this Genex
透過這個跟這個Genex
so go find this
所以去找到這個
Then this item is already in referring’s hands
那這個東西事實上已經在referring的手裡
So we just write a letter saying
所以我們只要寫一封信說
that this
那個這個
find is
找到的就是
New England Journal of Medicine
New England Journal of Medicine
The gene found in the magazine is our gene
雜誌上找到的基因就是我們這個基因
So this will be unlocked soon
所以這個就很快被解鎖
actually
其實
story behind that is
story behind that 就是
at this
在這個
There is a marker near our gene
我們的這個基因的附近有一個marker
Use their data with this generalized data
用他們的data用這個generalized data
look this his this
看起來的這個他的這個
Lot score
Lot score
His significance is in fact
他的significance 事實上是
better than this
還比這個
This I-L7R is still high
這個I-L7R還來的高
It means more significant
就是更significant的意思
at the same time
同時呢
What about the two GINs?
這個兩個GIN呢
actually very close
其實是非常靠近
This is the I-L7R
就是這個I-L7R
With this SL C1S
跟這個SL C1S
actually very close
實際上非常近
So what about this paper?
那所以這個paper呢
it's easy to accept
就很容易接受
But here
不過在這的話
One thing this Person is complaining about
有一點這個Person有點抱怨
Actually this I-L7R
其實這個I-L7R
I'll go back and check
我再我回去查
Because the sound is very deep
因為音響特別深刻
Just check my E-mail
就是查到我的E-mail
I sent my Corelibrator in an e-mail
我在一封E-mail給我的Corelibrator
In fact, there is a special mention of this
其實有特別提到這個
I tell everyone yes
我跟大家講說是
Between this GIN and this GIN
這個GIN跟這個GIN中間的話
very short gap
差距很短
Then this is also very important GIN
那這個也很重要的GIN
can they do something
是不是他們可以去做一些
This Validation and the like
這個Validation之類
but they didn't do it
可是他們沒有去做
The reason is because of that E-mail
那原因是因為那一封E-mail
Bounced back
被bounce回來了
they didn't send out at all
他們根本沒有送出去
so this
所以這個
But he might not be able to do it even if they are the same generation.
不過就是他們雙代他也不見得會做
because the words here
因為這裡的話
Sometimes it's later
有些時候都是後來比較
We still have a project that is working on this new era
我們目前還有一個project是在做這個新時代的
It is solid playful
就是solid playful
what about here
那這邊呢
There is more information involved
牽涉到的這個資料就更多了
We do Geneexpression probably
我們做Genexpression大概
Get the sneeper array of 30,000 Gene
弄的三萬Gene這個sneeper array
like this next generation
像這個next generation
Its output this data output is
它的output這個data output是
200 MacBits and more
200個MacBit等等
This is a very large data
這是很大型的資料
So behind this needs a big ID team to do it
所以這背後需要一個很大的一個ID team來做
Then we have some computer
然後我們有一些computer
use some of this
用一些這個
Through some clusters and so on
透過一些cluster等等的
do something like this
去做這樣子的一個東西
Then we also have a very good note
然後我們還有很不錯的注意
he may not be here
他也許不在這裡面
but he designs
但是他做設計
The most important thing is to hope that here can
最主要就是希望這裡頭能夠
through some information
透過一些資訊的方法
Accidents that can happen automatically
能夠自動出的意外
Because what we often encounter when dealing with these problems is
因為我們處理這些問題常常碰到的就是
you do something today
你今天做一些東西
do something tomorrow
明天做一些東西
If there is no system
那如果說沒有系統的出來
error prone
常常會有人容易出錯
If this error occurs, it will affect many
那這一出錯的話就會影響到很多
so everything
所以一切東西
We're all about wanting to be able to
我們講究的是希望能夠
online
online
Can use online code to get it out
能用online code 能弄出來
If you are right, you will always be right
對的話就永遠會對下去
If you are wrong, of course you will always be wrong
錯的話你當然永遠錯下去
So you have to be very, very careful when you first start
所以你剛開始的時候就要非常非常小心
After that, it doesn't matter
那以後的話就是不管
Today is this person's operation, tomorrow is that operation
今天是這個人操作明天是那個操作
you won't have
你就不會不會有
This information will be passed on
這個資料上面傳來傳去就會
generate some errors
產生一些錯誤
so information
所以資訊
Engineering talents help our lab a lot
工程的人才幫我們的lab 非常多
Then I want to end with this thing
那我想以這個東西來做一個結束
in 2004
在2004年
this
這位
Professor Joe Cohen
Joe Cohen的教授
he is
他是
one of rockfellow
rockfellow的一個
very famous population
很出名的population
Professor of Genetics
的genetics的教授
He wrote articles like this
他寫了這樣子的文章
The picture itself is very obvious
這個picture本身就很顯悟
Mathematics is
Mathematics is
biologist's next microscope only better
biologist's next microscope only better
biologist's mathematics next physics only better
biologist's mathematics next physics only better
that means yes
那意思就是說是
in biology
在生物學上面
Is it a problem in many trees?
是不是很多樹裡上面的問題
are developing
都在開發
After that, there will be more and more business
那以後的事業會越來越多
So this is a pretty important direction
所以這是一個相當重要的方向
That
那
Almost over
快結束了
Then this liquid association
那這個liquid association
Here is a profile from this creature
這是一個從這個生物上面的資料
Concepts developed
研發出來的觀念
Can it be used in other contacts?
那他在是不是可以用在其他contact
I'm sure there are many places to use
我相信有很多地方可以用
Actually, I told my daughter before
那其實我以前跟我女兒說
I want to explain what this liquid association is
想解釋看這個liquid association是什麼
Just think about your relationship with your friends
就講你想想看你跟你朋友的關係
good relationship sometimes
有時候關係很好
That's like repository creation
那就是像是pository creation
but when you're in a bad mood
可是當你心情不好的時候
The machinery is broken
機械都是搞壞了
Then your relationship with him may be
那你跟他的關係可能就是
So your positive negative
所以你的這個 positive negative
Does it change with your mood or how?
是隨著你的心情還是怎麼樣改變
Sometimes it will be positive and sometimes it will be negative
有時候會是 positive 也有時候是 negative
look at it from another angle
那換一個角度來看
look at another question
換一個問題來看
It should be a few days from now
現在應該是過幾天之後
Many people may have to take the exam
就可能很多人要配考
Then you see from the exam
那你從考試來看
Your preparation time and your grade
你準備的時間跟你的這個 grade
Is it effective?
是不是有效果
You may talk to your children, friends
你可能跟你的孩子啊 朋友啊
noisy for a long time
吵了半天
Sometimes it works
有時候說有效啊
Sometimes it doesn't work
有時候沒效啊
The more you prepare, of course the grades will come.
準備越多當然成績會啊
I have been preparing for half a day
我準備了半天
But these many different backgrounds
可是這些很多不同的 background
For example, a state of health
比方說是健康的狀態
If you say you are in good spirits
你如果說精神很好的時候
you are of course very effective
你當然是非常有效
The more you prepare, the better your grades
準備越多的話成績越好
then your health is not good
那你健康情況不好
you have been sick
你本來一直在病了
Then you'll be wasting your time if you're ready.
那你要是準備就白讀了
Then maybe there is no correlation
那說不定就沒有 correlation
or have cross-correlation
或是有互相關
So this idea that liquid has learned
所以這種 liquid 所學的觀念
is actually quite common
其實是相當普遍
almost in personal life
幾乎在個人的生活上面
He can use various
他可以用到各種不同的
This data, its calculation method is also very simple
這個資料 那它計算方法也很簡單
In that regard, I think this
那這方面的話 我想這個
Basically the relationship between these two variables
基本上就是這個兩個變量的關係
In fact, is it forever?
事實上是不是永遠一層不變的
then i want to carry the message here
那我想在這裡就帶這個訊息
OK everybody
OK 各位
That's some relevant information
那這是一些相關的資料
If you are interested, go and see
各位如果有興趣的話去看
Then I want to thank some past colleagues
然後我要感謝一些過去的同事
And then there are colleagues who are currently working on this
然後還有目前的這個工作的同仁
And this Haida team
還有這個海大團隊
There is also this Director of Combat Skills who can turn around in the sea
還有這個海中容轉的戰技成主任
And provide us with a lot of information
還有提供我們很多的資料
ok thank you everyone
好 謝謝各位
Thanks
謝謝
What's your problem?
你看各位有什麼問題
I would like to ask a question, now we are making the entire genetic line of the wedding paper in Taiwan
請教一個問題,現在我們在台灣有在做婚紙整段基因的定系
Came to find this Target Drog Dachanghai seems to have a special achievement
來找這個Target Drog大腸海好像是特別有成績
But the cost is very high, and health insurance costs more than 20,000 yuan
但是那個費用非常高,健保不幾乎要兩萬多塊
I think this will have a relatively stable price in the future around your research journal
我覺得這個是不是在你的研究刊圍將來會不會有比較平穩的價錢
or expand to other cancers
或者再擴大到其他的癌症
I think you may be asking the wrong person.
我想你大概可能問錯人了
Because we do statistics, I can't help
因為我們是做統計的,我沒辦法
I guess our job is to help people who develop
我想我們的工作是在幫忙開發的人
Then maybe be able to find a more effective marker
然後也許能夠找到更有效的marker
If you only need the proper information
那你只要適當的資料的話
If those markers say that elder brother lost
那些marker如果說是阿哥輸過
not much and very effective
不多同時非常有效
In fact, its price should be much lower than that of
那其實它的價格應該可以相對的比降低很多
so this is
所以這是
Eventure will also have
Eventure也會有就是
The ultimate goal, of course
終極的目標當然一些
The whole method should be quite civilian
整段方法都要相當平民化
So these things like genetic testing are still
所以這些像透過基因的檢測還是
the future is if it really works really
將來是如果說真的有效真的
It's really easy to promote
真的是很容易推廣的東西
Must be pretty cheap when mass produced
大量製造之後一定是相當便宜的
like i just mentioned
像我剛剛提到的
EGFR Mutation on lung cancer
EGFR Mutation這個肺癌上面
Now I listen to that Professor Yang
現在我聽那個楊教授講
You have been judged as lung adenocarcinoma
你這樣被判斷是肺腺癌
Especially if you are a gland, you will definitely make one like this
尤其是腺腺的話一定會做這樣子的一個
Pest
Pest
EGFR TEST
EGFR TEST
Because there are already medicines over there that can target this aspect
因為已經有藥在那邊可以針對這個方面
Then our current work is mainly aimed at
那我們的工作目前的工作主要是在針對
Of course that medicine is effective, but not everyone is effective
當然那個藥有效,但是不是每個人來都有效
still some people are bad
還是有些人差
Now it's just the gas meter
那現在是光那個定氣表
He wants more than 20,000 yuan
他就要兩萬多塊
Just look for that gene's calmness
就找那個基因的定氣
Calm down, I don't know about the holidays
定氣,假期我不是不知道
Thank you
謝謝你
Hello, Professor, I would like to ask
教授,您好,我想請問一下
Questions about experiments
關於實驗方面的問題
Professor, I just said that liquid sometimes learns to choose
教授,剛剛說到那個liquid有時候學學選
The professor mentioned that he needs many conditions
教授是提到說他需要很多條件的
That Error to find out the Target
那個Erroy去找出這個Target
Well, I have two questions
那這,我兩個問題
One is to say how many conditions are needed to do this
一個是說這個需要多少種condition去做
Then there is the second question
那還有第二個問題是說
like this is to do it yourself
那像這個是要自己做
Or is there some online
還是是不是有網路上有一些
It may be that someone else shares it for analysis.
可能是別人share的去做分析就好了
i think that
我想那個
in two programs
分兩個程式
One is to tell you how to do it
一個是說你到底這個方法
When can some interesting results be found
什麼時候可以找出一些有趣的結果來
Or the results that are believed in by statistics
或者是統計上面實在相信的結果來
How much condition does this need
這需要多少的condition
This depends on your liquid itself first
這個是看你這個liquid首先本身的
About the size of your earring
大概大小你的那個耳錠
If it is a student of Liquid, his strength is very high
如果是liquid所學生他的強度很高的話
Then the conditions you need will not be very big
那你需要的條件就不會很大
Then we did an analysis before
那我們做以前做過一個分析
About the same number of conditions
大概差不多條件的個數
Probably around 50 or so
大概差不多在50左右就可以了
If the fifth is
那第五是的話
Roughly the results obtained are statistically
大致上得到的結果在統計上面
Probably none that reaches a certain level of salience
可能沒有那個達到一定的這個顯著性
this is this one
這是這是一個
According to our semiation study
根據我們一個semiation study
Is it possible to use the data of this public domain
那是不是可以用這個public domain的data
my answer is yes
我的答案是肯定的
Because the first one is useless
因為第一個不用白不用
With the lady over there, you can get it out and you can
有了小姐那邊你弄出來你可以
some relationships can be found
可以找出一些關係來
and then further confirm
然後再進一步做確定
that in fact we are
那事實上我們是
like the examples I just gave
像我剛剛舉的這些例子
is an example of Multiple Squares
是Multiple Squares的例子
That's exactly Public Domain stuff
那完全就是Public Domain的資料
at the same time
那同時的話
Now maybe your own personal laboratory
現在可能你自己個人的實驗室
Take some data yourself
你自己照一些data
that amount may not be much
那量可能不太多
Then you can find some examples of genes
那你可以找到一些基因的例子
Moderators can go further with these little experiments
主持人可以更進這些小的實驗
I found several genes
我找到幾個基因
Then you have to go further
然後你要更進入
Go and see the genes related to the influence of these genes
去看看跟這個幾個基因有影響相關的基因
You can go to the Internet to look up more information about this performance
你可以到網路上去查更大的這個表現的資料
Then through this method
然後透過這種方法
come with SIMELE
來的用SIMELE
Students who use Corealization or Request
用Corealization方式或Request所學生
In fact, our lab uses both
事實上我們實驗室兩個都用
Then you can get some more information
然後就可以多一些訊息
then bring it back
然後就帶回來
Then you can take your experiment a step further
然後可以把你的這個實驗做進一步
So these are auxiliary
所以這些都是輔助的
or tools
或是工具
Hello teacher, thank you for your lecture
老師你好 謝謝您請教的演講
i want to ask
我想請教就是說
When using liquid association
在用liquid association的時候
There are a lot of situations coming out
有一堆狀況出來
but i think
可是我想
According to what you just said
依照您剛剛的說法
It seems that there are at least three situations
好像至少要分三種狀況
Positively correlated positively correlated with each other
正相關互相跟正相關
Of course if this
當然就是如果這個
positive correlation and positive correlation
正相關和正相關
There are also positive correlations with each other
還有正相關跟互相
or the one of omniscience and interrelationship
或是全知性跟互相關的那個
If the demarcation point is not adjusted properly
分界點沒有調好的話
In fact, the data is still messy
實際上資料還是很亂
That
那
At the beginning of the research
一開始在研究的時候
For example, how did the professor find out
比方說教授自己是怎麼樣去找出
How to cut those states
怎麼樣去切那幾個狀態
OK
OK
the cutting words
那個切割的話
because our theory is
因為我們的理論是
no need to cut
不需要經過切割
we're thinking of it as this
我們是把它想像成這個
state is a continuous state
狀態是一個連續的狀態
Then through some calculus methods
然後透過一些微積分的方法
go get it out
去把它弄出來
so
所以
It's not that it's OK, I'll cut to this side, to this side
不是說是OK我先切到這邊切到這邊
then compare
然後去比較
That is
那是
I originally thought the same way
初步的想法我原來也是那樣想
But want to say like you just said
但是想說就像剛剛你講
Then I have to cut 50%
那我到底要切50%
or 30%
或者30%
how is it possible
還是怎樣可能
Every gene is different
每個基因每個基因都不一樣
Well, that's actually what we saw in the end.
那事實上我們最後看出來也是那個樣
so that's why this
所以這是為什麼這個
Well
呃
do some math with words
做一些數學的話
There are always some people whose problem is
總是有一些人的問題就是
oops
哎啊
Although uh intuitive
雖然呃直覺上用
It is easier to think about it with this discrete method
用這個discrete方法比較容易去想
But doing the math above is to think of it as a continuous
但是做數學上面是把它想起來一個continuous
will be easier
會比較容易
So here, the whole sear
所以在這邊的話整個sear
this definition of mathematics
這個數學的這個定義
is to use an assumption to say that this change
是用一個假設說是這個變化
In fact, the change of state is a continuous change
實際上state的變化是一個連續型的變化
Then it has normal discretion
然後它有normal的discretion
Then through a lema called a stine
然後透過一個叫做stine的lema
that's professor of stine fire
那是stine火的教授
then he does some
然後他做一些
uh director
呃導演
And then at the end of the day to quit that simple company
然後到最後才能退出那個簡單的公司
and then to the last words
然後到最後的話
Then find out how to cut this gene
然後找出來這個基因之後我要怎麼切的話
that's easier
那就比較容易了
You can try it with
你可以用嘗試的辦法
We are on our computing workstation
我們在我們的計算的工作站上面
On the Internet, we do two ways
網路上面我們是做兩個辦法
One is to use the Maxmolecular method
一個是用Maxmolecular的辦法
The other is to use Discrete
另外一種是用Discrete
directly to calculate
直接去算
Director Li's speech is wonderful
李所長講的真精彩
i meet you after the afternoon
我下午以後我碰到你的話
Won't go there again...
不會再往那個...
run away
跑掉的
i have two questions
我有兩個問題
The first one is about the lung cancer thing you just talked about
第一個是關於你剛剛講的肺癌的事情
Later you also mentioned that non-smoking women have a high incidence of incidents in Taiwan
後來你也提到說不吸煙的女性在台灣的 incident 成高
Are these five signature genes related to that?
這五個signature gene是不是跟那個有關係
That is to say, did you subset when analyzing?
就是說你們在分析的時候是不是有沒有 subset 一下
See which respects are in the end
看看是到底哪一些respect
with that...
跟那個...
that...
那個...
The paper of the five genes, I think they didn't do the classification like that at that time
五個基因的那個paper 我想他們那時候並沒有做那樣子的分類
At that time, according to the title, he just flew the small one
那時候 根據title來講的話 他只是飛小型的這個
that lung cancer
那個 肺癌
For this classification, it is divided into this adinocasinoma
這個分類的話 就是把分成這個adinocasinoma
is our latest job
是我們最近的這個工作
And then our latest work is now this adinocasinoma
然後我們最近的工作是 即現在這個adinocasinoma
At the same time, it is based on whether he has EGF ammutation
同時又把它根據 他是不是有EGF ammutation
Let's do a comparison and then look at the formula on his molecule
來去做比較 然後去看他分子上面的程式
So what are you still doing because it's important
所以你們還在繼續做什麼 因為這是很重要
I heard that only the ones in Taiwan have this kind
我是聽說還養只有台灣的這個有這種
In comparison, there are actually a lot of Asians
比較說 其實亞洲人都很多
For Japan, there are a lot of things to wait for
對 日本啊等等的都很多
But there is a fundamental
但是裡頭存在的一個基本上面
That is, Teacher Ya and the others are most interested in it.
就是 亞老師他們那邊最感興趣了
That is, although everyone has discussed a lot about the connection method
就是雖然大家都討論很多這個依接法
Anyway, I think this Adino Castiglino
還是怎麼樣 都是認為這個Adino Castiglino
It was Adino Castiglino who was only recently recognized as
是Adino Castiglino是最近才被公認成
of a new form
一種新的形態的
In the past, it was probably mixed with Squamers
在以前的話大概跟Squamers還是混在一起
recent words
最近的話
So according to the world this is just an international organization
所以根據世界這個只是國際組織的話
Have had it tested on the ring saying it's a
已經把它戒指驗成說它是一個
So in this piece
所以在這一塊裡頭的話
At present, what I want to know most is
目前的話最想知道的是
According to Mutation and without Mutation
依接法Mutation跟沒有依接Mutation的話
what is the difference
到底差別在哪裡
It's not just a single Mutation that makes the difference
它不會只是單一個Mutation就會那麼差別
There are already many other classics in the surrounding area that have followed suit
已經有周邊很多的其他的經典跟著變化
That's what I'm currently working on
那就是我目前正在研究
So we base this
所以我們就根據這個
Copy number of variation and gene expression等等
Copy number of variation and gene expression等等
I believe many people are waiting to see
我相信很多人是拭目以待
this very important program
這個很重要的方案
The most important thing is to need a large sample
最主要還是需要很大的sample
the most important
最重要的
I have another question is
我還有一個問題是
about for example
關於譬如說
When it should have been broken
應該原來破題的時候
It is Messy data
是Messy data
In fact, for biologists
事實上對biologist來講
A lot of it is that the system itself is very messy
很多是system本身就是very messy
So it's not easy to do experiments
所以做實驗上不是很容易的
part i believe many
一部分我相信很多
biological data
biological data
Without doing statistics
在沒有做statistics
because make it last and equal to one
因為做出來最後and equal to one
There are many times when we do experiments
有很多時候我們做實驗
Because a lot of money
因為很多就是經費
or resources limit
或者resources限制
hardly anyone says
幾乎很少有人說
do an experiment to repeat
做到一個實驗去重複
Experiment twenty times can
實驗二十遍能夠
到statistically significant
到statistically significant
so i don't know
所以我不曉得說
developments in this area
現在這方面的發展
Said whether it has reached a certain level
說有沒有能夠到了一個程度
So can biologist
所以可以對biologist
some suggest
有些建議說
How to use the least method
怎麼樣可以用最少的方法
results that can be obtained
能夠得到的結果
able to be treated like this
能夠被這個treat like
Statistically significant data like this
statistically significant data這樣子
because you know now
因為你現在很清楚
final result
最後結果
A while ago they found out that
前一陣子他們發現說
Almost even if it's a different company
幾乎即使是不同的公司
with the same data
用同樣的 data
The results of these cups are about 40 to 50 completely different
這些的杯子所成的結果差不多有40到50完全不一樣
So, for example, by using your method to see
所以譬如說以假用你的方法來看
Could you please help us solve these problems?
能不能夠說用幫助大家解決這些問題
How to design an experiment
怎麼樣去設計實驗
I think your topic is very good
我想你這個題目是非常好的
Because you said N equal to 1
因為你說N equal to 1
In fact, many times although you have a lot of N
其實很多時候你雖然N很多
But the last words are only in the case of a N equal to 1
但是最後的話也是只不過在一個N equal to 1的情況之下
Because another experiment was placed
因為放了一個另外一個實驗
Although they took 100 pictures
雖然他們照了100片
But his N and N are under completely different circumstances
可是他的N跟N完全在不同的情況之下
Then this one is to think about it from the perspective of the network
那這個一個就是網絡觀的方面去想
That is to say, if today
就是說如果說是今天
Many units are willing to send money down
很多單位都願意發錢下去
Then do some more systematic design
然後做一些比較systematic的design
Then don't say you just thought of something
然後不要說是隨便想到什麼東西
just think of what to do
就想到做什麼
Between many N equal to 1
在很多的N equal to 1之間
can also have some hosts
還能夠有一些主持
will be better
會比較好一點
If so
那這樣子的話
you can combine different labs
你就可以結合不同的實驗室
A big M comes out like a string
一個像串出一個大M出來
that's there
那在
Now it is through the Internet
現在的話就是透過網路
a lot of this information
很多的這個資料
you can take it
你都可以把它
charge up
充電起來
Do some Metal Analyze
做一些Metal Analyze
I don't really like Metal Analyze
我不太喜歡用Metal Analyze
this idea
這個觀念
Because many times it is Trivial
因為很多時候都把它Trivial
ready to use
來使用好了
that means ok i do this
就是說OK我做這個
what to see
看到哪些東西
Significantly
有顯著
I will make it a PV
我就把它發生一個PV
those things have
那些東西有
Significantly
有顯著
Just post it as a PV
就把它發成一個PV
In the end you use a
到最後你去用一個
Same level company
同級公司
A PV that was born
生出來的一個PV
Actually Metal Analyze
其實Metal Analyze
its
它的
significance
意義
more than this
比這個更多
it should go to enalyze
它應該去好好地enalyze
After all
說到底
which laboratories
哪些實驗室
Why with which labs
為什麼跟哪些實驗室
Which laboratories will be the same
會相同哪些實驗室
with which labs
跟哪些實驗室
why is it different
為什麼會不相同
That
那
where is the same reason
相同原因在哪裡
or same reason where
或相同原因在哪裡
The reasons for these are the number of positions
那這些原因都是位置數
right
對不對
But the number of positions
可是位置數
if you have eyes
如果是有眼神
it will be
它會是
then no one knows
那誰也都不知道
So we can make an assumption
所以我們可以做一個假設
Perhaps these positions are
也許這些位置是
Maybe it can be expressed through some variables
也許可以透過某一些變量來表現
those variables maybe
那些變量也許
In fact, it may be the condition of the West
其實可以可能西方的condition
how like
怎麼樣怎麼樣的
Then these things can
那這些東西又可以
expressed by certain genes
被某些基因表現出來
So in fact there is a way
所以事實上是有辦法
When there were many genes
當年很多的基因的時候
Liquid Association
Liquid Association
in fact a
事實上是一個
I think
我想
The formula of Liquid Association is not necessarily necessary
不見得一定要Liquid Association這個公式
but the basic idea of ​​it
但是它的基本想法
It should be able to be used to manage
應該是可以被應用來管的
Because the most important thing is to find some potential factors
因為最主要就是要找一些潛在的因素
If the factors that existed before
那以前在的因素的話
Original words look
本來的話看起來
two time to make it
兩個時間做出來
The result is not related at all.
結果一點相關都沒有
that may be under certain conditions
那也許是在某些condition之下
they will have related
他們會有相關
ask your boss
請教你那個所長
just now you mentioned that
剛剛你有提到那個
Is it correct to match the big A with the small questions?
大A配題配小題對不對
That G type
那那個G配型
Then A and G are not compatible
那A跟G不能相配
That
那
If say cross match
如果說交差配
G matches T, A matches, okay?
G配T,A配型,行嗎?
G matching type, A matching type
G配型,A配型
Like this, is it possible?
這樣,可能嗎?
The No. 8 calculus seems to be forming wind
這個8號的結石,上面好像是形成風的樣子
So fixed A must match T
所以固定A一定要配T
Can't change the cross
不能改變交叉
No way, it has some chemical properties
沒辦法,那是有一些化學的性質
It's swords between each other, how about its attraction
它彼此之間的劍,怎麼樣它的吸引力
and its structure
還有它的結構
In fact, this is an important concept
事實上,這是一個很重要的觀念
In this way, it will be...
這樣子的話,才會…
It is this DNA that will make a pair and not mess up
就是這個DNA才會成雙,才不會亂
If it is not like that, then the structure is very unstable
如果不是那樣子的話,那這個結構上就很不穩定
Hello Professor
教授,你好
We are now working on the Biohometase part
我們現在在做Biohometase的部分
Generally speaking, there are two ways
我們一般來講,會有兩種方式
One is the statistical way you just talked about
一種是目前說,你剛剛講的統計的方式
It’s just that everyone compares it, and what many people are using is data mining.
就是大家比較就是也蠻多人在使用的就是 data mining
In your opinion, what is the biggest difference between these two people?
那在你的看法的話這兩個人覺得最大差異在什麼樣的地方
Or how do people feel that these two
或說有怎麼樣人覺得這兩個
Is there some kind of special opinion?
是覺得有什麼樣特殊的看法這樣子
ok that's a good question
ok 這個問題問得很好
That data mining is actually an informatics scientist
那個 data mining 事實上是資訊學家
I don't know if it was stolen
也不知道是不是偷去
Imagine a rather new way to develop statistics
想像出來一個相當替統計開發出一條新的道路來
because statisticians
因為統計學家
This statistic itself sounds like crying and tasteless
這個本身統計本來聽起來就哭著無味
data analysis sound analysis data
資料分析聽起來分析資料
to call out a
要叫出一個
How about BetaMade in Chinese?
BetaMade中文怎麼樣
data mining
就是資料採礦
Mining doesn't sound good.
這採礦其實不好聽啊
But carbon health is not good
不過碳康也不好
But English itself is very nice
但是英文本身就是很好聽
Yes or no
是不是
is data mining itself
就是 data mining 本身
I'm human so what do you think
我是個人這樣你覺得
data mining you turn it into data
data mining 你把它翻成資料
Do you want to poke around like the unminer?
你希望像那個沒礦工人那樣探開嗎?
Does that sound like a lot?
聽起來好多嗎?
It's not that hard, is it?
沒有那麼難吧對不對?
But DataMind is going to dig some information
但是DataMind要去挖掘一些information
A lot of statistical concepts are used there
那裡頭用到的是很多的統計的觀念
There are many things of course a computer scientist
有很多東西當然是computer scientist
himself according to his intuition
他自己根據他的直覺
can match many things
能夠把很多東西配出來的
these things
這些東西
Let's not talk about which school this is.
我們這邊也不要講說這個是到底哪一個學校
For example, DataMind uses a lot of support vector machines
比方說DataMind用的很多叫support vector machine
If it supports vector machine, it is used for classification
support vector machine的話它是拿來說classification
Vasus has a set of discreement like RFVsure
Vasus像RFVsure有一套discreement
Who is better then?
那來說誰的好?
So that actually depends on the structure of the different states
所以那實際上是因狀態不同的結構而定
When there is a lot of noise in the Vsure of RFVsure
RFVsure的Vsure裡面在資料比較很多noise的時候
it will be more effective
它會比較有效
SupportVeq's Machine is in the data
SupportVeq的Machine在資料
its this
它的這個
Less noise
Noise比較少
But the state is complicated
但是狀態很複雜
When the Covered Manifold is more complicated
它這個Covered Manifold比較複雜的時候
it will be more effective
它會比較有效
So each has many different degrees
所以各都有很多的不同程
That
那
concepts used
用到的觀念
you could say statistics
你可以說是統計
aka mathematics
也可以說數學
anyway
還是怎麼樣的反正
It's all logic
都是一些邏輯上面
A methodical approach to data analysis
對數據一個有條理的分析方式
so it can be useful in certain situations
所以它會在特定的情況之下有用
OK
好的
besides
還有
close first
先關一下
we today
我們今天
this page you know so far
這一頁你知道這裡為止
thanks again
我們再次謝謝
Thank you Zhou Da
謝謝周大